<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd" [
]>

<webpage id="about-redistribution">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD Licensing and Redistribution"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: redistribution.xml,v 1.4 2009/08/16 14:36:16 hubertf Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2009/08/16 14:36:16 $"/>
<head>
<title>NetBSD Licensing and Redistribution</title>
</head>

<para>
This page exists to give you a bit of
<ulink url="#copyright-info">background information about copyright</ulink>,
to <ulink url="#terms">explain the licensing terms</ulink> that most of
the NetBSD operating system is distributed under, and to
<ulink url="#why">explain why we chose those licensing terms</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1 role="toc">

<sect2 id="terms">
<title>NetBSD's copyright and licensing terms</title>

<sect3 id="berkeley">
<title>The traditional Berkeley license</title>

<para>
For the most part, the software constituting the NetBSD operating
system is not in the public domain; its authors retain their copyright.
However, because the people working on the NetBSD Project
are committed to providing a
free operating system, the license terms that cover most of the
Project's source code
are relatively lenient.  In general, developers pattern their license
terms after what's known as the <quote>Berkeley license</quote>.  This license
was used in the University of California, Berkeley's second Berkeley
Networking Release and the 4.4BSD Lite software release, and looks like
this:
</para>

<programlisting>
Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
are met:

  1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
  2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
     notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
     documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
  3. Neither the name of the University nor the names of its contributors
     may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software
     without specific prior written permission.
</programlisting>

<para>
The license is preceded by the copyright statement itself, and
is followed by some disclaimer information, so that
if someone has problems with the software the authors can't be
held liable.
</para>

<para>
The Berkeley license is a rather liberal license.  All it requires
is that the author of the work be given due credit for their creation,
and that their name not be used to promote products based on their
work.  It allows free distribution, as long as the terms are followed,
and also allows people to modify the work and <emphasis>not</emphasis> 
distribute it, if they so choose.  Some contributors also omit the third 
clause.
</para>

<para>
Though the Berkeley license is generally used as the template for
the license
terms of works that are part of the NetBSD source tree, it does not
apply to all works in the source tree, and you should check the
individual source files to see what license applies to them.  In
particular, certain parts of the source tree are covered by the
<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"><emphasis role="bold">GNU General Public License</emphasis></ulink>
(also known as the <emphasis role="bold">GPL</emphasis>),
which is very different from the Berkeley license.  Though
we would like all of the software that we distribute
to be covered by a Berkeley-style license,
we can't make other people change their license terms, and we don't
have an infinite amount of time to rewrite all of the software that
we need.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="default">
<title>Default license for all code assigned to The NetBSD Foundation</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Foundation's (TNF) license is a <quote>2 clause</quote> <ulink
url="#berkeley">Berkeley-style</ulink> license, which is used for all code
contributed to TNF.  If you write code and assign the copyright to TNF, this
is the license that will be used:
</para>

<programlisting>
/*-
 * Copyright (c) 2008 The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.
 * All rights reserved.
 *
 * This code is derived from software contributed to The NetBSD Foundation
 * by 
 *
 * Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
 * modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
 * are met:
 * 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
 *    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
 * 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
 *    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
 *    documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
 *
 * THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE NETBSD FOUNDATION, INC. AND CONTRIBUTORS
 * ``AS IS'' AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
 * TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
 * PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE FOUNDATION OR CONTRIBUTORS
 * BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
 * CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
 * SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS
 * INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN
 * CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE)
 * ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
 * POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
 */
</programlisting>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="why">
<title>NetBSD's choice of license</title>
<sect3 id="why-berkeley">
<title>Why the NetBSD Project uses a Berkeley-style license</title>

<para>
The people working on the NetBSD Project want to provide a
high-quality system that anyone can use for whatever they want.
We are not in it for the money (we are volunteers!), so we have no
desire to keep people from distributing our work.  However, neither do
we want to place our work into the public domain, and thereby give
up our claim to even having our names on the software we wrote!
</para>

<para>
One thing that some people don't realize about Berkeley-style
licenses is that they allow licensees (the users of the licensed work)
to sell the code, in any form, with or without modification, and that
they make no requirement that licensees give away the source code,
even if they're selling binaries.
This provides a striking contrast to the license
terms granted by the GNU General Public License, because the GPL requires
that, if you're distributing binaries, you must be willing
to give away the sources to build those binaries.
</para>

<para>
Those of us working on the NetBSD Project are aware of this
distinction, and some even value it.  As stated above, we want
<emphasis>anyone</emphasis> to be able to use the NetBSD operating system for
<emphasis>whatever</emphasis> they want, just as long as they follow the few
restrictions made by our license terms.  Additionally, we don't
think it's right to require people who add to our work and want to
distribute the results (for profit or otherwise) to give
away the source to their additions; they made the additions, and they
should be free to do with them as they wish.
</para>

<para>
In summary, the people involved in the NetBSD Project use a Berkeley-style
license where possible because it closely matches our goal of allowing
users to do whatever they'd like with our software, while still retaining
the copyright and getting credit for the work we have done.  We are
pragmatic, however, and will include software with different license terms
in the NetBSD operating system if it significantly improves the quality of
the system.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="why2clause">
<title>Why NetBSD switched from using a 4-clause to a 2-clause license</title>
<para>
In 2008, following on from a vote amongst the membership of the NetBSD
Foundation, and in recognition of the changing face of software
licensing, the NetBSD Foundation has changed its recommended license to be a
2 clause BSD license.  This recommended license is the
one that the NetBSD Foundation strongly encourages its contributors to use
when assigning copyright to the NetBSD Foundation.
</para>
<para>
At the same time, all the code which was contributed to the NetBSD
Foundation has been modified to use the new 2-clause NetBSD license.
</para>
<para>
The change in license has come about because of a number of factors:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      We have seen organisations and people concerned about the old clause
      3 (the advertising clause) in the license, to the extent where NetBSD
      code could not be used in commercial products; the new license means
      that these concerns are no longer valid.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      UCB moved some time ago to remove clause 3 from the code
      contributed to UCB; this change mirrors that one.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
     Some of our developers work for companies in Open Source or research
     departments where they are allowed to contribute back daytime work to
     the open source project, but only if the project's license is
     acceptable to their legal department, and the 4 clause BSD license
     has been rejected in some cases.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The members of the NetBSD Foundation (i.e. its developers) no
      longer considered clause 4 (the "endorsement" clause) to be useful
      in today's software world.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
Third parties are encouraged to change the license on any files which have
a 4-clause license contributed to the NetBSD Foundation to a 2-clause
license. We would also encourage you to inform us about these files, so that
we can continue to track the many places in which NetBSD is used.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="copyright-info">
<title>Copyright information</title>

<sect3 id="what-is">
<title>What is copyright, anyway?</title>

<para>
<emphasis role="bold">This information is for educational purposes only 
and we do not claim to provide legal advice.</emphasis>  If you need legal 
advice, you should talk to a lawyer licensed to practice in your area.  If
you would like more information about copyright than we provide
here, you may want to look at the
<ulink url="http://faqs.org/faqs/law/copyright/faq/">Copyright FAQ</ulink>,
but you should note that it doesn't provide legal advice, either.
</para>

<para>
Copyright is the mechanism that allows creators to obtain certain
exclusive rights to their creations.  For instance, it allows a poem's
author the right of exclusive reproduction of his or her poem; only the
creator of a work, or those given permission by the creator, may
reproduce that work.
Copyright protects original expression.  It does <emphasis>not</emphasis> 
protect the ideas or facts that underlie a work, nor does it protect
any pre-existing work that the creator of a work has incorporated into
their work.
In the United States and in other countries that are
signatories to the Berne Convention, a work's creator does 
<emphasis>not</emphasis> need to mark the work in any way to retain copyright.
</para>

<para>
The various protected rights to a work can be granted by means of a
<emphasis role="bold">license</emphasis>, a set of terms and conditions that 
define the situations
in which a third party may reproduce a creator's work.  The terms
of a license can vary greatly: some licenses demand a fee, while
others make no such requirement; some licenses restrict further
redistribution of a work, while others may <emphasis>require</emphasis> it in
certain conditions.
</para>

<para>
There are many ways that the terms of a license
can come into effect.  For instance, a license agreement may be signed
before access to a work is given, or a prominent statement of the license
terms may be made along with a statement that use of the work implies
acceptance of the license terms (known as a <emphasis role="bold">shrink-wrap 
agreement</emphasis>).
</para>

<para>
Note that there is a significant difference between works for
which a creator retains copyright and works that are placed into the
public domain by their creator.  When a creator places a work into the
public domain, he or she gives up <emphasis>all</emphasis> rights to the work 
in question.  An author of a piece of software cannot say something such
as, "This work is in
the public domain.  You may redistribute it freely as long as you do
not charge for it."  This is self-contradictory, because by placing
the work in the public domain, they gave up their right to control
its reproduction.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</webpage>
