<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
    "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="about-y2k">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD Year 2000 compliance"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: y2k.xml,v 1.2 2007/06/03 19:41:59 dsieger Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2007/06/03 19:41:59 $"/>
<head>
<title>NetBSD Year 2000 compliance</title>
</head>


<sect1 id="top">

<para>
We have audited and (where necessary) corrected the following classes
of code:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Programs which only accepted 2-digit year numbers have been
    corrected to accept 4-digit years as well.</listitem>
<listitem>Programs and library functions which accept 2-digit year numbers
    interpret years 00-68 to be prefixed with 20 (i.e. 2000-2068),
    per the recommendation of the Single Unix Specification.</listitem>
<listitem>Programs and library functions which output year numbers have been
    verified to output years past 1999 correctly.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
To the best of our knowledge, NetBSD 1.3.1 and later are year 2000 compliant.
</para>

<para>
If you have any additional questions, you can send mail to
<email>tech-userlevel@NetBSD.org</email>.
To report a year 2000 bug, please submit a
<ulink url="support/send-pr.html">problem report</ulink>
in the <emphasis role="bold">y2k</emphasis> category using 
&man.send-pr.1; on your NetBSD system, or fill out our
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/sendpr.cgi?gndb=netbsd">send-pr form</ulink>
on the web.
</para>

<para>
Please note that our auditing efforts do not guarantee that third party
software run under NetBSD is year 2000 compliant.  If you have concerns
about this, please contact the author or vendor of such software
separately.
</para>

<sect2 id="quick-hints">
<title>Quick hints for year 2000 compliance tests</title>

<para>
Here are some suggestions for testing your scripts and third party software
for year 2000 compliance:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Back up your system first, if having "future" dates in logfiles or
    file system time stamps or such would cause you any trouble.</listitem>
<listitem>Disable any clock synchronization you have running (ntpd, timed, etc).</listitem>
<listitem>Manually set the system's clock to 1999-12-31 23:00:00.</listitem>
<listitem>Test your applications work through "midnight 1999".</listitem>
<listitem>Switch the machine off.</listitem>
<listitem>Test that the machine correctly boots in the new century.  (Some PC BIOSes
    may have difficulties.)</listitem>
<listitem>Check that applications start up and function correctly.
    Pay particular attention to scripts that use 'date' with '%' formats;
    scripts using %Y should be fine, those using %y likely are not.</listitem>
<listitem>Set the date back, and restore any backups if necessary.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
There are two other dates that are known to be problematic:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><emphasis>9 September 1999</emphasis><html:br/>
    Some programmers used 9-9-99 as an unreachable end condition, while in fact
    it is a valid date. We are now past this hurdle without any reported
    NetBSD problems.
</listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>29 February 2000</emphasis><html:br/>
    The first leap year. (or the last leap year of this century if you want
    to get too technical) which some incorrect algorithms do not correctly
    handle.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Please note that this is not intended to be a comprehensive set of instructions
for testing year 2000 compliance.  For mission critical systems, you should
seek guidance from an expert.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<parentsec text="About the NetBSD Project" url="about.html" />

</webpage>
