<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
    "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="Documentation-software-compiling">
<config param="desc" value="Installing/compiling other software"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: compiling.xml,v 1.5 2005/09/08 21:20:36 heinz Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2005/09/08 21:20:36 $"/>
<head>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1994-2005
	The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.  ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. -->
<title>Installing/compiling other software</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="top">

<table border="0" id="top-table">
<tr>
  <td align="left">
<para>
This page used to contain instructions on how to build and install software
under NetBSD.  Since in general, we <emphasis role="bold">strongly</emphasis>
recommend you make use of the many software packages available in the <ulink
url="packages.html">NetBSD packages collection</ulink>, you will only find
very limited additional information on this page.
</para>
  </td>
  <td align="right" valign="bottom">
  <ulink url="../../Misc/disclaimer.html#bsd-daemon">
    <html:img align="middle" src="../../images/BSD-daemon.jpg" border="0"
      width="146" height="129" alt="BSD daemon"/></ulink>
  </td>
</tr>
</table>
</sect1>

<sect1 role="toc">

<sect2 id="compiling-downloading">
<title>Compiling/downloading software</title>

<sect3 id="java">
<title>How to run java programs under NetBSD</title>
<para>
There are a number of java <ulink url="packages.html">packages</ulink>
available in the NetBSD Packages Collection, including the latest JDKs from
Sun (<filename role="pkg">lang/sun-jdk13</filename>, 
<filename role="pkg">lang/sun-jdk14</filename>,
<filename role="pkg">lang/sun-jdk15</filename>).  The Sun JDKs currently run under <ulink
url="../compat.html">binary emulation</ulink>, while others (such as
<filename role="pkg">lang/kaffe</filename> and 
<filename role="pkg">lang/wonka</filename>) run natively.
</para>
<para>
You can also build your own native Sun JDK by following the instructions
available from <ulink url="http://www.eyesbeyond.com/freebsddom/java/"/>.
Don't let the name mislead you -- these instructions are entirely applicable
to <emphasis>Net</emphasis>BSD as well!
</para>
<para>
At some point in the future it may be possible for The NetBSD Project to
provide native Sun JDK builds;  however, at the moment the licensing terms of
Sun's JDK prohibit us from doing so.  We will update this documentation when
the situation changes.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="precompiled_packages">
<title>Where to find precompiled programs</title>
<para>
Precompiled binary packages for the various NetBSD ports are available through
the <ulink url="packages.html">NetBSD Packages Collection</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="elf-issue">
<title>3rd party Software that I compiled myself doesn't find its shared libraries!</title>
<para>
An issue which often is encountered when trying to compile software initially
written for other Unices, is the problem with the program not finding its
shared libraries. This is due to the philosophy of NetBSD's <ulink
url="../elf.html#elf">ELF</ulink> implementation. This is a known problem, and
there exists a <ulink url="../elf.html#rpath">resolution procedure</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
Of course, The Right Thing To Do is to install all software using <ulink
url="packages.html">the NetBSD Packages Collection</ulink>.  If the software is
not yet available in pkgsrc, you can either &man.send-pr.1; a report or build the
package yourself.  You can find more information in the <ulink
url="../pkgsrc/">pkgsrc documentation</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<parentsec url="./" text="NetBSD Documentation: Software"/>
</webpage>
