<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd" [
]>

<webpage id="disclaimer">
<config param="desc" value="Disclaimers and Copyright Information"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: disclaimer.xml,v 1.10 2005/05/05 08:09:08 hrs Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2005/05/05 08:09:08 $"/>
<head>
<title>Disclaimers and Copyright Information</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="top">
<title>Disclaimers</title>

<para>
The content on this server is maintained by The NetBSD Project.  The
server machine itself is hosted by <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/">Internet
Software Consortium (ISC)</ulink> and managed by Paul A. Vixie, Michael Graff
and Philip A. Nelson.
<emphasis>Neither The NetBSD Project nor ISC make any
guarantees as to the currency, accuracy, or quality of information
stored here.</emphasis>
If misleading or otherwise inappropriate information is brought to our
attention, a reasonable effort will be made to fix or remove it.  Such
concerns should be addressed to
<ulink url="/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
The NetBSD Project would like to thank ISC for hosting this server.
</para>

<para>
All brand or product names are or may be trademarks of, and are
used to identify products and services of, their respective owners. 
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="copyright-information">
<title>Copyright Information</title>

<sect2 id="netbsd-site">
<title>NetBSD WWW Site Copyright</title>
<para>
Except where otherwise noted, the contents of this server are copyright
1994-2005 by The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.  All rights reserved.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="code">
<title>Code Copyright and Licensing information</title>
<para>
Please see <ulink url="../Goals/redistribution.html">this page</ulink> for
details regarding the copyright and licensing terms under which The NetBSD
Foundation releases their code.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="netbsd-flag">
<title>NetBSD Flag Copyright</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Flag image was drawn as an entry in the NetBSD logo contest.
Ownership of the image was transferred to The NetBSD Foundation, and the
image and any parts thereof are Copyright (&copy;) 2004 by The NetBSD
Foundation. All rights reserved. Non-commercial and personal use of the image
is permitted, provided that it remains unmodified. Mass production, commercial
use, or use of a modified copy of the image requires explicit written
permission. Permission may be obtained by writing to The NetBSD Foundation at
<email>board@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="netbsd-daemons">
<title>NetBSD Daemons Copyright</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Daemons image and any parts thereof are copyright
1994 by Shawn Mueller.  All rights reserved.  Non-commercial and personal
use of the images is permitted, provided that it remains unmodified.
Mass production, commercial use, or use of a modified copy of the
image requires explicit written permission.  Permission may
be obtained by writing to:
</para>

<address>
Shawn Mueller (BA, BSc, MES)
<email>mullrs@yahoo.com</email>
c/o #202, 817 - 5 Street N.E.
Calgary, AB CANADA
T2E 3W9
</address>


</sect2>

<sect2 id="bsd-daemon">
<title>BSD Daemon Copyright</title>
<para>
BSD Daemon Copyright 1988 by Marshall Kirk McKusick.
All Rights Reserved.
</para>

<para>
Permission to use the daemon may be obtained from:
</para>

<address>
Marshall Kirk McKusick
<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
1614 Oxford St
Berkeley, CA 94709-1608
USA
</address>

<para>
Questions and comments should be directed to <ulink
url="/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

</webpage>

