<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="Misc-disclaimer">
<config param="desc" value="Disclaimers, Trademark and Copyright Information"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: disclaimer.xml,v 1.17 2005/11/25 04:14:19 hubertf Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2005/11/25 04:14:19 $"/>
<head>
<title>Disclaimers, Trademark and Copyright Information</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="top">
<title>Disclaimers</title>

<para>
The content on this server is maintained by The NetBSD Project.  The
server machine itself is hosted by <ulink url="http://www.isc.org/">Internet
Software Consortium (ISC)</ulink> and managed by Paul A. Vixie, Michael Graff
and Philip A. Nelson.
<emphasis>Neither The NetBSD Project nor ISC make any
guarantees as to the currency, accuracy, or quality of information
stored here.</emphasis>
If misleading or otherwise inappropriate information is brought to our
attention, a reasonable effort will be made to fix or remove it.  Such
concerns should be addressed to
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
The NetBSD Project would like to thank ISC for hosting this server.
</para>

<para>
NetBSD<superscript>&reg;</superscript> is a registered trademark of
The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.
All brand or product names are or may be trademarks of, and are
used to identify products and services of, their respective owners. 
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="copyright-information" role="toc">
<title>Copyright Information</title>
<sect2>

<sect3 id="netbsd-site">
<title>NetBSD WWW Site Copyright</title>
<para>
Except where otherwise noted, the contents of this server are Copyright
(&copy;) 1994-2005 by The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.  All rights reserved.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="code">
<title>Code Copyright and Licensing information</title>
<para>
Please see <ulink url="../Goals/redistribution.html">this page</ulink> for
details regarding the copyright and licensing terms under which The NetBSD
Foundation releases their code.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="the-netbsd-logo">
<title>The NetBSD logo</title>
<para>The NetBSD Flag image was drawn as an entry in the NetBSD logo
contest. Ownership of the image was transferred to The NetBSD Foundation
and the image and any parts thereof are Copyright (&copy;) 2004 by The NetBSD Foundation.
All rights reserved. Permission to use the NetBSD logo is subject to the
terms and conditions in the <ulink url="#logo-usage">NetBSD Logo Usage Guidelines</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="logo-usage">
<title>NetBSD Logo Usage Guidelines</title>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Definition of terms</title>
    <simplelist type="vert">
    <member>
<quote lang="en">The NetBSD Logo</quote> is the copyrighted graphic artwork at
<ulink
url="../images/NetBSD.png">http://www.NetBSD.org/images/NetBSD.png</ulink>.
    </member>

    <member>
      The <quote lang="en">Powered by NetBSD</quote> logo
      is the copyrighted graphic artwork at
      <ulink url="../images/powered-by-NetBSD.png">http://www.NetBSD.org/images/powered-by-NetBSD.png</ulink>
    </member>
    </simplelist>
  </formalpara>
</listitem>

<listitem>
  <formalpara>
    <title>The NetBSD Logo</title>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
          <title>Non-commercial use</title>
	  <para>
The NetBSD Project hereby licenses The NetBSD Logo for non-commercial
products and non-commercial web sites.
Acceptable non-commercial use of The NetBSD Logo includes:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
As a logo to identify NetBSD-related web pages, e.g. if licensee
is a NetBSD user or NetBSD supporter,
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
As a logo to identify NetBSD-related content in presentations given
at conferences.
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

The following use of The NetBSD Logo is not
acceptable, and no license is granted for such use:

	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
Use is unrelated to The NetBSD Foundation, to The NetBSD Project,
or to the NetBSD operating system,
	      </listitem>

	      <listitem>
The logo is used in a detrimental way for The NetBSD Foundation.
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>

The NetBSD Foundation reserves the right to revoke this license at any
time.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>


      <listitem>
	<formalpara>
          <title>Commercial use</title>
	  <para>
The NetBSD Foundation is under certain circumstances willing to license
The NetBSD Logo for certain commercial products,
services, and web pages.
To inquire about the commercial use of The NetBSD Logo,
please send email
to <email>logo@NetBSD.org</email> with a description of the product, service,
or web site, indicating where and how you'd like to use The NetBSD Logo.
	  </para>
	</formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </formalpara>
</listitem>


<listitem>
  <formalpara>
    <title>The Powered by NetBSD Logo</title>
    <para>
The NetBSD Project hereby licenses The Powered by NetBSD Logo for
commercial and non-commercial products and web sites provided that
they are powered by the NetBSD operating system or make use of the
pkgsrc packages system.

The NetBSD Foundation reserves the right to revoke this license at any
time.
    </para>
  </formalpara>
</listitem>


<listitem>
  <formalpara>
    <title>Additional Legal Terms and Conditions</title>
    <para>
Any reprinting, sublicensing, modifying, publishing, assignment, transfer,
sales, or other distribution of The NetBSD Logo and The Powered by NetBSD Logo,
 in parts or as a whole, is strictly prohibited without the prior written
consent of The NetBSD Foundation.

The NetBSD Logo and The Powered by NetBSD Logo are to be used "as it appears"
and must not be cut up or materially altered without prior written permission
of The NetBSD Foundation.

Any copyright notice, digital watermark or proprietary legend contained
in or on the logo must not be altered or removed.

Unauthorized copying of the NetBSD logos or failure to comply with any
of the terms, restrictions, conditions, or limitations herein will result
in automatic termination of this non-exclusive license.

These terms of this agreement are subject to change without notice.
    </para>
  </formalpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-daemons">
<title>NetBSD Daemons Copyright</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Daemons image and any parts thereof are Copyright (&copy;)
1994 by Shawn Mueller.  All rights reserved.  Non-commercial and personal
use of the images is permitted, provided that it remains unmodified.
Mass production, commercial use, or use of a modified copy of the
image requires explicit written permission.  Permission may
be obtained by writing to:
</para>

<address>
Shawn Mueller (BA, BSc, MES)
<email>mullrs@yahoo.com</email>
c/o #202, 817 - 5 Street N.E.
Calgary, AB CANADA
T2E 3W9
</address>


</sect3>

<sect3 id="bsd-daemon">
<title>BSD Daemon Copyright</title>
<para>
BSD Daemon Copyright (&copy;) 1988 by Marshall Kirk McKusick.
All Rights Reserved.
</para>

<para>
Permission to use the daemon may be obtained from:
</para>

<address>
Marshall Kirk McKusick
<email>mckusick@mckusick.com</email>
1614 Oxford St
Berkeley, CA 94709-1608
USA
</address>

<para>
Questions and comments should be directed to <ulink
url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
</sect1>

</webpage>

