<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
    "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="Misc-pr-states">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD Problem Report States"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: pr-states.xml,v 1.5 2005/07/16 17:13:44 heinz Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2005/07/16 17:13:44 $"/>
<head>

<title>NetBSD Problem Report States</title>
</head>


<sect1 id="page-top">

<para>
Each PR goes through a defined series of states between origination and
closure. The submitter of a PR receives notification automatically via E-mail of
any state changes.
</para>

<sect2 id="open">
<title>open</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
The initial state of a Problem Report. This means the PR has been filed
and the responsible person(s) notified.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="analyzed">
<title>analyzed</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
The responsible person has analyzed the problem. The analysis should
contain a preliminary evaluation of the problem and an estimate of the
amount of time and resources necessary to solve the problem. It should
also suggest possible workarounds.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="feedback">
<title>feedback</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
The problem has been solved, and the submitter has been given a patch
or other fix.  The PR remains in this state until the submitter
acknowledges that the solution works.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="suspended">
<title>suspended</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
Work on the problem has been postponed. This happens if a timely
solution is not possible or is not cost-effective at the present time.
The PR continues to exist, though a solution is not being actively
sought. If the problem cannot be solved at all, it should be closed
rather than suspended.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="dead">
<title>dead</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
Work on the problem has been permanently abandoned.
This state is for problems where there is no possible way to continue
examining the PR, e.g.  someone reported that their machine crashed
once, in an old version of NetBSD, and could never reproduce it;
someone no longer has the hardware needed to reproduce the problem.
The purpose of the "dead" state, as distinct from the "closed" state,
is so that people searching the database can quickly ascertain that a
problem is not known fixed.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="closed">
<title>closed</title>
<para>
<blockquote>
A Problem Report is closed ("the bug stops here") only when any
changes have been integrated, documented, and tested, and the submitter
has confirmed the solution.
</blockquote>
</para>
</sect2>

<html:hr/>
<ulink url="#page-top">[Page&nbsp;top]</ulink>
<ulink url="../Gnats/">[GNATS&nbsp;summary]</ulink>
<ulink url="query-pr.html">[Query&nbsp;PR]</ulink>
<ulink url="pr-fields.html">[PR&nbsp;fields]</ulink>
<ulink url="pr-hints.html">[PR&nbsp;hints]</ulink>

</sect1>
</webpage>
