<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
    "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="contrib-index">
<config param="desc" value="Contributions to the NetBSD project"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: index.xml,v 1.12 2008/01/04 19:49:18 dsieger Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2008/01/04 19:49:18 $"/>
<head>
<title>Contributions to the NetBSD project</title>
</head>

<table width="100%" id="intro"><tr>
<td align="left">
<para>
This page contains methods of helping the
NetBSD project, if you have any questions or comments,
please let us know at <email>www@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>
</td>
<td>
<ulink url="../about/disclaimer.html#bsd-daemon">
<html:img align="middle" src="../images/BSD-daemon.jpg" border="0"
width="146" height="129" alt="BSD daemon"/></ulink>
</td></tr></table>

<sect1 id="top">

<!--   <note> -->
<!--     <title>The NetBSD Fundraising Campaign 2007</title> -->
<!--     <para><emphasis role="bold">Please support the NetBSD Fundraising Campaign 2007. -->
<!--       Read more about the goals and the current state of the campaign on  -->
<!--       <ulink url="../donations/">our donations page</ulink>.</emphasis> -->
<!--     </para> -->
<!--   </note> -->
  
  <para>
    As a non-profit organization, The NetBSD Project is an organization
    which relies on the valuable contributions of individuals, companies 
    and other organizations.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Contributions to NetBSD include money, hardware to support new
    platforms and peripherals, rack space to support critical project
    services, funding developers and more.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    In addition, some organizations and individuals contribute money and staff
    for promotional events such as trade shows.  Some trade show organizers
    also provide free or low-cost space.
  </para>

  <para>
    The easiest way to donate is of course 
    <ulink url="../donations/">monetarily</ulink>. More 
    ideas and methods to contribute are listed below.
  </para>

  <para>There's also a <ulink url="projects.html">list of projects</ulink>
    we would like to see implemented in the operating system. If you want
    to contribute, this is a good place to start.
  </para>
</sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="thankyou">
    <title>Thanks a lot for your contribution to the NetBSD project!</title>

    <para>
      We have a <ulink url="org/">gallery of companies</ulink> that assist the
      project, and would be very much interested in hearing from you at 
      &lt;<ulink url="mailto:www@NetBSD.org">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>&gt;.
    </para>

    <para>
      A list of people and companies that have donated previously to our
      project is available from
      <ulink url="../donations/">our donations page</ulink>.
    </para>

  </sect1>


<sect1 role="toc">
<title>How you can contribute</title>
<!-- TOC generated here -->

<html:hr />

<sect2 id="system">
<title>The system</title>

<sect3 id="feedback">
<title>Use the system and make suggestions</title>
<para>
First of all, NetBSD is a user supported project, so your <ulink
url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">feedback</ulink> is very welcome. This
includes comments, patches, new code as well as documentation. Feedback
can be given via the <ulink url="../support/send-pr.html">problem report
system</ulink>, and is also welcome on the various <ulink
url="../mailinglists/">mailing lists</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="report-bugs">
<title>Report problems and suggestions</title>
<para>
If you have any problems and suggestions, <emphasis>please</emphasis> submit them to our
<ulink url="../support/send-pr.html">problem report database</ulink>. You can either
use the &man.send-pr.1; program installed on any NetBSD machine, or use the
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/sendpr.cgi?gndb=netbsd">online form</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
We cannot emphasize how important it is to use the problem report database -
if you just send the bug report or suggestion to a mail list it can fall
through the cracks.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="submit-fixes">
<title>Submit fixes and code</title>
<para>
Fixes and new code are passed into the same database as <ulink
url="#report-bugs">bug reports</ulink>. The database can be browsed at
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/Gnats/">http://www.NetBSD.org/Gnats/</ulink>.
You can pick an entry from the database to analyze and submit the
fix back in E-mail to <email>gnats-bugs@NetBSD.org</email> with the Problem
Report Number as the subject, and your contribution will be
automatically added to the problem report.
</para>
<para>
You can also help <ulink url="#pkgsrc">adjusting 3rd party
applications</ulink> to run (better) on NetBSD, by helping out with the <ulink
url="../docs/pkgsrc/">NetBSD Packages Collection, pkgsrc</ulink>.
There are more than enough open problems in the "pkg" category in Gnats (see
above), and if that's not enough, more outstanding items can be found in
<currentsrc>pkgsrc/doc/TODO</currentsrc>. If there's no PR for a
package/problem yet, try talking to the maintainer before opening a PR.
</para>
<para>
Do not worry if you do not have commit access to the source tree,
the responsible person(s) will review it, and if it looks good to
them, will probably commit the fix.  (Note that only the PR and
the responsible person(s) will receive a copy of your message.
Unless you explicitly send them a copy, the submitter and other
interested parties will not be automatically sent a copy)

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="submit-new-code">
<title>Contribute new code</title>
<para>
NetBSD may have the most portable source tree in the world, but
there is always scope for more drivers and new ports. From small
utilities' enhancements to complete ports to new hardware architectures,
good code is always welcomed.
</para>
<para>
There is a <ulink url="../developers/features/">list of features</ulink> supported by each
port, and sometimes additional work in getting all ports up
to the latest &amp; greatest is greatly appreciated!
</para>
<para>
If you are working on a relatively small change the best approach
is to produce a set of patches, using "diff&nbsp;-u&nbsp;-N" or
"cvs&nbsp;diff&nbsp;-u&nbsp;-N", and to submit them in a <ulink
url="../support/send-pr.html">PR</ulink>. (-N will allow patch to work
for added files).
</para>
<para>
For larger changes it may be easier to put up the patches for anonymous
ftp, and include a URL in the <ulink url="../support/send-pr.html">PR</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
If you are working on a port to new hardware it would be appreciated
if you could contact <email>core@NetBSD.org</email>, so you can be informed of
anyone else working on the same goal.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="submit-documentation">
<title>Contribute Documentation</title>
<para>
Good documentation is crucial for the success of the NetBSD Project. That is
why we try to maintain the highest standard with respect to our man-pages,
example configuration files and online documentation.  The
documentation available on your NetBSD system is maintained under CVS control
just like the code, so if you encounter typos or mistakes, you can use the same
approach as for
<ulink url="#submit-new-code">submitting code changes</ulink>.
Similarly, this website and all the <ulink url="../docs/">online
documentation</ulink> is under CVS control - you need to checkout the
<emphasis>htdocs</emphasis> module to make direct changes and submit
patches.
</para>

<para>
If you are not familiar with CVS source trees,
the documentation formats, or htdocs, you can and shall still contribute:
For suggestions and changes regarding the NetBSD Guide, a man page or any
other document, just submit a description or a draft to the 
<email>netbsd-docs@NetBSD.org</email> mailing list. For changes or 
additions  to the NetBSD website, write a note to
<email>www@NetBSD.org</email>, the internal  mailing list of the www
team. Please submit changes or drafts as plain text.
</para>

<para>
The NetBSD Project maintains only the English version of the
documentation. If you are fluent in both English and another
language, you might be interested to translate existing
documentation and to maintain the translation independently.
Refer to the
"<ulink url="../developers/translate.html">Translating htdocs</ulink>"
web page for more details.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="track-netbsd-current">
<title>Track NetBSD-current</title>
<para>
<ulink url="../releases/current.html">NetBSD-current</ulink> is a daily
snapshot of the NetBSD development source tree.  If you can, testing
-current and submitting <ulink url="../support/send-pr.html">bug reports</ulink>
is a great way to help.  Instructions for testing -current
can be found in the <ulink url="../docs/current/">Tracking
NetBSD-current</ulink> documentation.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="test-patches">
<title>Test Developer Patches</title>
<para>
Often NetBSD developers wish to test new code before putting it into
the source tree, but can't sufficiently do so by themselves.  By joining
the <ulink url="../mailinglists/#tech-kern">tech-kern</ulink> <ulink
url="../mailinglists/">mailing list</ulink> you can find out when a
developer would like people to try out a new patch, and where the
patch is available from.
</para>
<para>
Since the patch is not integrated with the NetBSD source tree yet,
you shouldn't use the <ulink
url="../support/send-pr.html">NetBSD bug tracking system</ulink> for reporting
any problems you may have.  Instead, if you have any problems or general
comments you wish to convey, you should either e-mail the developer
who has created the patch, the mailing list they announced it on, or
both.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="finance-support">
<title>Hire consultants or developers for specific support</title>
<para>
If you are interested in paying for specific support or features, there are
a number of <ulink url="../gallery/consultants.html">consultants</ulink> available,
from drivers for specific hardware, to security, and systems integration.
</para>

<para>You can hire NetBSD developers to work on in-house NetBSD 
 projects.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="new-architectures">
<title>Port to new architectures</title>
<para>
<ulink url="../ports/#suggested-ports">See this page for details</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc">
<title>Third party packages</title>
<para>
While most free software will compile on NetBSD 'out of the box',
the <ulink url="../docs/software/packages.html">NetBSD packages
system</ulink> handles installation, dependencies and easy removal for
hundreds of packages.  If you find something not already covered
by the package system, maybe even contribute back the information
to make a package yourself. To contribute a package use the supplied
send-pr(1) command or <ulink
url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/sendpr.cgi?gndb=netbsd">online
form</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="projects">
<title>NetBSD Projects</title>
<para>
A list of non-trivial projects that would benefit NetBSD is available <ulink
url="projects.html">here</ulink>.
If you are proposing to pick up one of the projects, esp. as part
of things like the Google Summer-of-Code, you may want to have a 
look at our
<ulink url="soc-application.html">project application howto</ulink>
that gives some questions that are intended to
help you and us get a grip on the project.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<html:hr/>

<sect2 id="donations">
<title>Donations</title>

<sect3 id="hardware">
<title>Hardware needed/available</title>
<para>
<ulink url="hardware.html">See this link</ulink>
 for details about needed hardware or available but not yet supported hardware.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="hardware_companies">
  <title>If your company produces hardware</title>
  <para>
    From interface cards to complete machines, two of the greatest
    hurdles to supporting hardware are availability of technical
    documentation, and access to the hardware itself. If your organisation
    can provide either of these to NetBSD developers it can help NetBSD
    users worldwide, and benefit your company image.
  </para>

  <para>
    Those companies that wish to assist further can contribute specific
    code for drivers which can reduce the NetBSD 'time to market' for
    the product and ensure the hardware is used to its full advantage.
  </para>

  <para>
    A statement as to the degree of support available for NetBSD can
    increase NetBSD users' confidence in selecting a given product.
    Even if direct support is not available, information as to in-house
    testing with NetBSD will encourage users to choose a product over
    a competitor who does not perform such testing.
  </para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="paypal">
<title>How to donate money to NetBSD</title>
<para>
<ulink url="../donations/">See this link for details</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="developer-resources">
<title>Shell accounts for NetBSD development</title>
<para>
Rick Kelly, <email>rmk@rmkhome.com</email>, has created the <ulink
url="http://www.rmkhome.com/NetBSD/">NetBSD Developer Resources</ulink>
page, which lists NetBSD users who will donate time on their machines
to increase awareness of NetBSD and widen the pool of available software
for the OS.  
</para>
<para>
If you'd like to add yourself to the listing of those who would be willing
to offer shell accounts on their NetBSD systems for use in NetBSD
development, please visit Rick's listing for more information.
</para>
<para>
As an alternative, there's also an
<ulink url="http://www.allbsd.org/#pub-shell">offer of shell accounts</ulink>
from the <ulink url="http://www.allbsd.org/">AllBSD</ulink> project.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<html:hr/>

<sect2 id="online-information">
<title>Online information</title>

<sect3 id="NetBSD.org">
<title>The NetBSD.org web site</title>
<para>
If you find anything out of place, or any suggestions for the NetBSD.org
site, please <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/cgi-bin/feedback.cgi">let us know!</ulink>

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="mirror">
<title>Maintain FTP mirror servers</title>
<para>
If you have disk and bandwidth to donate, running a mirror FTP server
would be helpful.
The most important resource for mirrors is storage space.
See our <ulink url="../docs/mirror.html">mirroring FAQ</ulink>
for an estimate of required disk space and further information.
Contact <ulink url="mailto:mirrors@NetBSD.org">&lt;mirrors@NetBSD.org&gt;</ulink>
for more details.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<html:hr/>

<sect2 id="advocacy">
<title>Advocacy</title>

<sect3 id="netbsd-advocacy">
<title>netbsd-advocacy mail list</title>
<para>
There is a <ulink
url="../mailinglists/#netbsd-advocacy">netbsd-advocacy</ulink>
list specifically for discussion on promoting the NetBSD project
and the use and knowledge of NetBSD in general.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="daemon-news">
<title>Write news and articles for Daemon News</title>
<para>
<ulink url="http://www.daemonnews.org/">Daemon News</ulink> welcomes
articles about all things BSD. If you have written something
that might be of general interest, send it to
<email>articles@daemonnews.org</email>.
</para>
<para>
If you have any BSD-related news, submit it to
<ulink url="http://daily.daemonnews.org/">Daily Daemon News</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
Daemon News is always looking for new people, so if you want
to help running the magazine, you should consider
<ulink url="http://staff.daemonnews.org/">joining the team</ulink>.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="hardware_vendors">
<title>Web sites selling old and new hardware</title>
<para>
As suggested by Erik E. Fair <ulink
url="mailto:fair@clock.org">&lt;fair@clock.org&gt;</ulink> and Joel
Reicher <ulink
url="mailto:joel@panacea.null.org">&lt;joel@panacea.null.org&gt;</ulink>.
Many vendors sell hardware, both old and new, but are unaware of the
fact it can run NetBSD. A link between their site and www.NetBSD.org
can benefit both parties.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rc5">
<title>The NetBSD RC5 team</title>
<para>
<table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="95%" id="rc5-table"><tr><td>
  <ulink url="mailto:explorer-rc5@flame.org">Michael Graff</ulink> set up a
  NetBSD team at <ulink url="http://www.distributed.net/">distributed.net</ulink>
  to work on the RSA labs RC5 and DES challenges
</td><td>
  <ulink url="http://www.distributed.net/"><html:img
  src="../images/links/dnet.gif" border="0" width="88" height="32"
  alt="moo-logo"/></ulink>
</td></tr></table>
</para>
<para>
The client software computes a part of the key space, making use of the
spare cycles of your computer, running at the nicest CPU level. 
Under normal conditions, the only noticeable effects of the client would
be the load average is &gt; 1 and the mails the client sends you from time
to time.
</para>
<para>
It would be nice if you would also join our NetBSD team, even if you
don't run NetBSD on your computer.
</para>
<para>
Links on joining the NetBSD RC5 team:
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink
      url="http://stats.distributed.net/team/tmsummary.php?project_id=8&amp;team=4420">Team
      summary</ulink> for our team</listitem>
  <listitem>The <ulink
      url="http://stats.distributed.net/team/tlist.php?project_id=8&amp;low=1&amp;limit=100">top
      100</ulink> teams</listitem>
  <listitem>Unofficial <ulink url="http://www.flame.org/netbsd-rc5/">NetBSD clients</ulink>
      at flame.org</listitem>
  <listitem>Official <ulink
      url="http://www.distributed.net/download/clients.html#nbsd">NetBSD
      clients</ulink> at distributed.net</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="seti">
<title>The NetBSD SETI@home group</title>
<para>
<table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" id="seti-table"><tr><td>
  <ulink url="http://setiathome.ssl.berkeley.edu/">SETI@home</ulink> is a
  scientific experiment that will harness the power of hundreds of
  thousands of Internet-connected computers in the Search for
  Extraterrestrial Intelligence (SETI).
</td><td>
  <ulink url="http://setiathome.ssl.berkeley.edu/"><html:img
  src="../images/links/seti.gif" border="0" width="100" height="35"
  alt="seti-logo"/></ulink>
</td></tr></table>
</para>
<para>
You can participate by running a
program that downloads and analyzes radio telescope data. There's a
small but captivating possibility that your computer will detect the
faint murmur of a civilization beyond Earth. There is a specific <ulink
url="http://setiathome.ssl.berkeley.edu/stats/team/team_12172.html">NetBSD
group</ulink>, which you can join by selecting the 'Join this Group' link
at the top of that page. Seti@home is available as 
<filename role="pkg">net/boinc3-seti</filename>
from pkgsrc.

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-logos">
<title>Include a NetBSD logo on your site</title>
<para>
If your web server runs on a NetBSD box, then why not include one of the
<ulink url="../gallery/logos.html">NetBSD logos</ulink> (Caution: NetBSD logos
document is image intensive).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="merchandise">
<title>Proudly wear NetBSD merchandise</title>
<para>
NetBSD has its own <ulink url="http://www.cafepress.com/NetBSD/">Cafepress
Online Store</ulink> selling various products such as shirts, sweatshirts, a
mug, wall clock, mousepad, logo magnets, and tote bags.
All profits from this online store will be used to directly fund NetBSD!
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</webpage>
