<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="releases-formal-3-NetBSD-3.0.2" release="3.0.2">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD 3.0.2 Release Announcement"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: NetBSD-3.0.2.xml,v 1.5 2009/06/10 23:12:25 dent Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2009/06/10 23:12:25 $"/>
<head>
<title>Announcing NetBSD 3.0.2</title>
</head>

<para>
The NetBSD Project is pleased to announce that version 3.0.2 of the
NetBSD operating system are now available in both source and binary
form.
NetBSD is a general-purpose Open Source operating system that provides
interfaces for running a wide range of applications on a big number of
different hardware platforms, all from one source tree.
NetBSD 3.0.2 contains a selected subset of critical bugfixes and
security updates over NetBSD 3.0.</para>

<sect1 id="about-netbsd-3.0.2">
<title>About NetBSD 3.0.2</title>

<para>
NetBSD 3.0.2 is the second security/critical update of the NetBSD 3.0
release branch. This represents a selected subset of fixes deemed critical
in nature for stability or security reasons.
</para>

<para>
All fixes in security/critical updates (ie, NetBSD 3.0.1, 3.0.2, etc) are
cumulative, so this latest update contains all such fixes since the NetBSD
3.0 release.  These fixes also appear in the 3.1 release and future releases
(ie, NetBSD 3.2, 4.0, etc), together with other less-critical fixes and
feature enhancements.
</para>

<para>
Complete source and binaries for NetBSD 3.0.2 are available for
download at many sites around the world. A list of download sites providing
FTP, AnonCVS, SUP, and other services is provided at the end of this
announcement; the latest list of available download sites may also be found
at <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/mirrors/">http://www.NetBSD.org/mirrors/</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
We encourage users who wish to install via a CD-ROM ISO image to download
via BitTorrent by using the torrent files supplied in the ISO image area.
BitTorrent has recently been added to the list of distribution mechanisms
and its use is strongly encouraged to help keep bandwidth available.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="about-netbsd">
<title>About NetBSD</title>

<para>
NetBSD is a general-purpose Open Source operating system that provides
interfaces for running a wide range of applications on a big number of
different hardware platforms, all from one source tree.
Applications
can range from proprietary closed source applications to Open Source
software, covering desktop environments, database servers, firewalls,
routers, embedded appliances and many more, all made available easily
through pkgsrc, the NetBSD Packages Collection, which currently
contains over 6.300 packages.
Picking up its ancestry from the Berkeley Networking Release 2
(Net/2), 4.4BSD-lite and 4.4BSD-Lite2, the NetBSD project continues to
provide its application platform on a wide range of hardware platforms
- not only vintage hardware, but also modern desktop and server
hardware with Intel and AMD Opteron CPUs as well as embedded systems
with MIPS, PowerPC, Super-H, ARM and Xscale CPUs. More recently,
NetBSD was also ported to "virtual" hardware provided by the Xen
machine monitor. Today, NetBSD runs on 54 different system
architectures featuring 17 machine architectures across 17 distinct
CPU families, all from a single source tree. In addition, the system
offers cross compiling for the kernel, userland and the X Window
system.
</para>

<para>
The NetBSD 3.0.2 release contains complete binary releases for 53
different machine types, and support for four more machine
architectures in source form. 
</para>

<para>
More information on the goals of the NetBSD Project can be procured from the
NetBSD web site at <ulink url="../../about/">http://www.NetBSD.org/Goals/</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
NetBSD is free. All of the code is under non-restrictive licenses, and may
be used without paying royalties to anyone. Free support services are
available via our mailing lists and web site. Commercial support is
available from a variety of sources; some are listed at <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/gallery/consultants.html">http://www.NetBSD.org/gallery/consultants.html</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
More extensive information on NetBSD is available from the NetBSD web
site <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/">http://www.NetBSD.org/</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
NetBSD is the work of a diverse group of people spread around the world. The
`Net' in our name is a tribute to the Internet, which enables us to
communicate and share code, and without which the project would not exist.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="changes-301-302">
<title>Major Changes Between 3.0.1 and 3.0.2</title>

<para>
The complete list of changes can be found in the CHANGES-3.0.2 file in the
top level directory of the NetBSD 3.0.2 release tree.
</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Kernel <itemizedlist><listitem>Avoid a panic in page fault handling that could occur under low-memory conditions. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem>Networking <itemizedlist><listitem>Changed the default &man.sshd.config.5; to enable SSH version 2 only. </listitem><listitem>Don't accept TCP connections to broadcast addresses. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem>File system <itemizedlist><listitem>Fixed race condition in NFS renaming that could cause the renamed file to be deleted. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem>Libraries <itemizedlist><listitem>When a user is created, initialize the string of secondary groups to avoid it containing garbage when none is added. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem>Security
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>Fixed a buffer overflow in the in-kernel PPP code share by ISDN PPP interfaces &man.ippp.4; and &man.pppoe.4; (SA2006-019). </listitem>
	    <listitem>X11: fixed an integer overflow in FreeType (SA2006-020).</listitem>
	    <listitem>Fixed a potential DoS attack with &man.sendmail.8; (SA2006-017). </listitem>
	    <listitem>Fixed a DoS vulnerability in BIND (SA2006-022). </listitem>
	    <listitem>Fixed a RSA signature forgery in &man.openssl.1; (SA2006-023). </listitem>
	    <listitem>X11: fixed a vulnerability in Adobe Type 1 font handling (SA2006-021). </listitem>
	    <listitem>Fixed a number of DoS vulnerabilities in &man.openssl.1; (SA in preparation, CVE entries: 2006-2937, 2940, 3738 and 4343). </listitem>
	    <listitem>Fixed a number of DoS vulnerabilities in &man.sshd.8; (SA in preparation, CVE entries: 2006-4924 and 5051). </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
        <listitem>Miscellaneous <itemizedlist><listitem>Fixed cross-building from hosts using GCC 4.x. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../ports/amd64/">amd64</ulink> specific <itemizedlist><listitem>Make sure that the system reboots after a panic instead of halting. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../ports/sparc/">sparc</ulink> specific <itemizedlist><listitem>Disabled threading in &man.named.8; on sparc and sparc64 to avoid a crash. </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../ports/mac68k/">mac68k</ulink> specific <itemizedlist><listitem>sysinst now newfs'es and mounts the target filesystem(s). </listitem></itemizedlist></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="ack">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>

<para>
The NetBSD Foundation would like to thank all those who have contributed
code, hardware, documentation, funds, colocation for our servers, web pages
and other documentation, release engineering, and other resources over the
years.  More information on the people who make NetBSD happen is available
at <ulink
url="http://www.NetBSD.org/people/">http://www.NetBSD.org/people/</ulink>. 
</para>

<para>
We would like to especially thank the University of California at Berkeley
and the GNU Project for particularly large subsets of code that we use. We
would also like to thank the Internet Systems Consortium and the Helsinki
University of Technology for current colocation services.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="about-tnf">
<title>About the NetBSD Foundation</title>

<para>
The NetBSD Foundation was chartered in 1995, with the task of overseeing
core NetBSD project services, promoting the project within industry and the
open source community, and holding intellectual property rights on much of
the NetBSD code base. Day-to-day operations of the project are handled by
volunteers.
</para>

<para>
As a non-profit organisation with no commercial backing, The NetBSD
Foundation depends on donations from its users, and we would like to ask you
to consider making a donation to the NetBSD Foundation in support of
continuing production of our fine operating system.
</para>

<para>
Donations can be done via PayPal <email>paypal@NetBSD.org</email> and are fully tax-
deductible in the US.  If you would prefer not to use PayPal, or would like
to make other arrangements, please contact <email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="mirrors">
<title>NetBSD mirror sites</title>

<para>
    Please use a mirror site close to you.
</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    	<listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#ftp">FTP</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#iso">ISO images</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#anoncvs">Anonymous CVS</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#bittorrent">BitTorrent</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#sup">SUP</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#cvsup">CVSup</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#rsync">rsync</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#afs">AFS</ulink></listitem>
        <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#nfs">NFS</ulink></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<para>
    Please also note our list of <ulink url="../../sites/cdroms.html">CD-ROM
    vendors</ulink>.
</para>
</sect1>


<parentsec url="./" text="NetBSD 3.x formal releases"/>
</webpage>
