<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
    "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="changes-2005">
<config param="desc" value="Changes and NetBSD News in 2005"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: 2005.xml,v 1.10 2010/03/21 18:21:00 jschauma Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2010/03/21 18:21:00 $"/>
<head>
<headlink rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="NetBSD news"
  href="http://www.NetBSD.org/changes/rss-netbsd.xml" />
<headlink rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="NetBSD code changes"
  href="http://www.NetBSD.org/changes/rss-netbsd-internals.xml" />
<headlink rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml" title="pkgsrc changes"
  href="http://www.NetBSD.org/changes/rss-netbsd-pkgs.xml" />
<title>Changes and NetBSD News in 2005</title>
</head>


<sect1 id="top">

<sect2 id="other-news">
<title>Changes in other years</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink url="index.html">Recent Changes and News</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2009.html">Changes and News in 2009</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2008.html">Changes and News in 2008</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2007.html">Changes and News in 2007</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2006.html">Changes and News in 2006</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="#200512">Changes and News in 2005</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2004.html">Changes and News in 2004</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2003.html">Changes and News in 2003</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2002.html">Changes and News in 2002</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2001.html">Changes and News in 2001</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="2000.html">Changes and News in 2000</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="1999.html">Changes and News in 1999</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="1998.html">Changes and News in 1998</ulink></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<html:hr />

</sect1>

<sect1 role="toc">

<sect2 id="200512">
<title>December 2005</title>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc2005q4-amd64">
<title>30 Dec 2005 -  NetBSD/amd64 binary packages for pkgsrc-2005Q4 available</title>
<para>
Jan Schaumann <ulink url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/port-amd64/2005/12/28/0000.html">has announced</ulink>
that <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal> binary packages for the
<port>amd64</port> port are now available, and have been uploaded to
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/3.0/amd64/" />.
Please use a <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/mirrors/">mirror</ulink>
site close to you.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc2005q4">
<title>30 Dec 2005 - pkgsrc-2005Q4 has been branched</title>
<para>The pkgsrc developers are very proud to announce the new
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal> branch, which has support for more
packages than previous branches. As well as updated versions of many
many packages, the infrastructure of pkgsrc itself has been improved
for better platform and compiler support, and also for enhanced
security. At the same time, the <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal> branch
has been deprecated, and continuing engineering starts on the
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal> branch.</para>

<para>The source tar files for the new branch can be found at:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/2005Q4/pkgsrc-2005Q4.tar.gz" /></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/2005Q4/pkgsrc-2005Q4.tar.bz2" /></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>You can also use the <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal> tag to check
it out yourself from anoncvs.NetBSD.org or any of the
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/mirrors/#anoncvs">mirrors</ulink></para>

<para>Please see the detailed <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal> announcement
in <ulink url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/12/27/0001.html">Alistair
G. Crooks's email</ulink> to the tech-pkg mailing list for more
information.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="cgd-interview">
<title>30 Dec 2005 - Inside NetBSD's cgd</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.onlamp.com/">O'Reilly ONLamp.com</ulink>
has published an
<ulink url="http://www.onlamp.com/pub/a/bsd/2005/12/21/netbsd_cgd.html">interview</ulink>
of Federico Biancuzzi with NetBSD's Roland Dowdeswell, discussing
the cryptographic disk driver, &man.cgd.4;, which was introduced by Roland
in NetBSD 2.0.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-3">
<title>23 Dec 2005 - NetBSD 3.0 released</title>
<para><ulink url="../releases/formal-3/">NetBSD 3.0</ulink>, the eleventh
major release of the NetBSD operating system, has been released with binary
distributions for 53 architectures.</para>
<para>NetBSD 3.0 continues our long tradition with major improvements in
file system and memory management performance, major
security enhancements, and support for new platforms and peripherals.</para>
<para>NetBSD 3.0 now features PAM (OpenPAM), TCP SACK, TCP MD5,
&man.pf.4;, IPsec ESP/IKE over NAT, IPv4 PIM, &man.tap.4; and much more
hardware support than before. Check the <ulink 
url="../releases/formal-3/NetBSD-3.0.html">release announcement</ulink> for more
detailed information.</para>

<para>Many of the FTP Mirrors are now carrying the NetBSD 3.0
distribution. Please try to use <ulink
 url="../mirrors/torrents/">BitTorrent</ulink> to retrieve the available
ISO images. If you can't, then download the ISO file directly from
the <ulink url="../mirrors/#ftp">NetBSD FTP Mirror Site</ulink>
closest to you.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-3rc6">
<title>12 Dec 2005 - NetBSD 3.0 RC6 available</title>

<para>In a <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/12/12/0000.html">message</ulink>
to the netbsd-announce list, &a.tron;, member of the NetBSD release
engineering team, announced the availability of NetBSD 3.0 RC6 on the FTP
server of the NetBSD project. This, hopefully, latest release candidate
fixes and updates some drivers and some last-minute corrections.
For a more detailed list of the latest changes please see &a.tron;'s original <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/12/12/0000.html">announcement</ulink>.
</para>

<para>For downloads of NetBSD 3.0 RC6, please consider one of the
<ulink url="../mirrors/#ftp-releng">mirrors</ulink> of the release engineering
FTP server.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-freeze-2005Q4-announced">
<title>06 Dec 2005 - Freeze of pkgsrc tree for pkgsrc-2005Q4</title>

<para>
In a <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/12/06/0010.html">message</ulink>
to the <ulink url="../mailinglists/#tech-pkg">tech-pkg mailing list</ulink>
&a.agc; announced that the NetBSD Packages Team will stop the development
of non-essential changes for pkgsrc to prepare for the release of the
next stable branch <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q4</literal>. The freeze period
will begin December 12th 2005 and is expected to last about two weeks.
During this period, the developers will bring down the number of open
problem reports and fix problems shown by the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/pkgsrc-bulk/">bulk builds</ulink>.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-nov-2005">
<title>02 Dec 2005 - Changes to the Packages Collection in November 2005</title>

<para>The monthly summary of pkgsrc activities has been <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/12/02/0001.html">published</ulink>
by &a.agc;. At the end of November pkgsrc contained 5737 packages, an
increase of 80 new packages from the previous month.
</para>

<para>The <quote>Package of the Month</quote> award goes to
<filename role="pkg">emulators/gxemul</filename>, an emulator capable of
running several different ports of NetBSD.
</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-3rc5">
<title>02 Dec 2005 - NetBSD 3.0 RC5 available</title>

<para>In a <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/12/02/0000.html">message</ulink>
to the netbsd-announce list, &a.tron;, member of the NetBSD release
engineering team, announced the availability of NetBSD 3.0 RC5 on the FTP
server of the NetBSD project. This latest release candidate solves
some security issues and fixes a few driver problems. For a more detailed
list of the latest changes please see &a.tron;'s original <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/12/02/0000.html">announcement</ulink>.
</para>

<para>For downloads of NetBSD 3.0 RC5, please consider one of the
<ulink url="../mirrors/#ftp-releng">mirrors</ulink> of the release engineering
FTP server.
</para>
<para>
In addition to the usual set of archive files there were also ISO images
created for NetBSD 3.0 RC5. 
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200512">
<title>01 Dec 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    &a.jnemeth; (login: jnemeth)
    will be working on PAM and miscellaneous tasks.
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    &a.kardel; (login: kardel)
    will be working on time counters and ntp.
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="200511">
<title>November 2005</title>

<sect3 id="netbsd-3-0-status">
  <title>29 Nov 2005 - Status of NetBSD 3.0 release</title>
  <para>
    &a.tron; of the NetBSD Release Engineering team has sent an <ulink
    url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/11/29/0000.html">update</ulink>
    on the status of the release process for NetBSD 3.0 to the mailing
    list netbsd-announce. The fifth release candidate (NetBSD 3.0_RC5)
    has been tagged in the CVS repository. Builds of this version are
    expected to be available later this week.
  </para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="new-pbn-logo">
  <title>24 Nov 2005 - New official <quote>Powered by NetBSD</quote> logo</title>

  <para>
    After switching to a new official NetBSD logo some time ago,
    an official logo for websites running NetBSD was not available. Thanks to
    the artistic skills of Jacek Kutzmann, NetBSD is now proud to announce the
    availability of the new official <quote>Powered by NetBSD</quote> logo.
    It can be used
    for commercial and non-commercial products and web sites provided that they
    are powered by the NetBSD operating system or make use of the pkgsrc
    packages system.
  </para>
  <para>
    Please see the 
    <ulink url="../foundation/press/new-powered-by-logo.html">press release</ulink>
    for more information, or see the 
    <ulink url="../gallery/logos.html">NetBSD Logos webpage</ulink>.
  </para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-3rc1">
  <title>18 Nov 2005 - NetBSD 3.0 RC1 available</title>
  <para>
    On behalf of the NetBSD Release Engineering team, &a.tron; has <ulink
    url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/11/18/0000.html">announced</ulink>
    that the release process for NetBSD 3.0 has officially begun. The first
    release candidate is available for download from daily builds.
    (The list of significant source changes from NetBSD 2.0 to
    3.0 is available <ulink url="changes-3.0.html">here</ulink>.)
  </para>
  <para>
    The second Release Candidate is expected to be available on the FTP server
    in about a week, and we hope this will be the final release candidate.  If all
    goes well the final release of 3.0 is only approximately three weeks away!
  </para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="donation-results">
<title>08 Nov 2005 - Donation Results</title>
<para>
A few months ago, the NetBSD Project made a <ulink url="#pledge0605">call for
donations</ulink>.  This was widely publicized, and our community of donors
responded extremely generously.  Over the next few months, we received
almost $30,000 of donations, including a number of donations of
several thousand dollars each.  As previously <ulink
url="#donations-status">outlined</ulink>, this money was earmarked for
specific purchases, and the NetBSD Project would like to let our users know
what in particular was bought from these generous donations.
</para>
<para>
&a.tls;, who initiated the original call for donations and who has put
countless hours into the entire process (including drawing up the
specifications, installating the hardware and configuring the
software), published <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/11/07/0000.html">this
detailed summary</ulink>, indicating exactly how the money was used.  Many
thanks to Thor and, again, all our donors!
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-2.1">
<title>02 Nov 2005 - NetBSD 2.1 released</title>
<para>
    <ulink url="../releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">NetBSD 2.1</ulink>,
    the first maintenance release of the
    <ulink url="../releases/release-map.html">netbsd-2</ulink> release branch,
    has been released with binary distributions for 48 architectures.
    More information is available in the <ulink
    url="../releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">2.1 release
    announcement</ulink>.
</para>
    <para>
    Many of the FTP Mirrors are now carrying the NetBSD 2.1 distribution.
    Please try to use the <ulink url="../mirrors/#ftp">NetBSD FTP Mirror Site</ulink>
    closest to you. In addition, we also encourage the use of
    <filename role="pkg">net/bittorrent</filename> to retrieve <ulink
    url="../mirrors/torrents/">all available ISO images</ulink>.
</para>
    <para>
    <ulink url="../ko/Releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">Korean</ulink>,
    <ulink url="../pt_BR/Releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">Portuguese</ulink>,
    <ulink url="../ru/Releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">Russian</ulink>,
    <ulink url="../es/Releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">Spanish</ulink> and
    <ulink url="../sv/Releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">Swedish</ulink>
    language translations of the NetBSD 2.1 release announcement are
    also available.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="sa-051102">
<title>02 Nov 2005 - New Security Advisories</title>
<para>
  <ulink url="../support/security/advisory.html">Security
  Advisories</ulink> 2005-003 through 2005-013 have been released on a range of issues.  The
  <ulink url="../releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.1.html">NetBSD 2.1</ulink> release contains fixes for most of these issues, but
  special attention is warranted on the most recent three, which did
  not make it into 2.1:
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SA2005-011.txt.asc">SA2005-011</ulink>
    affects the ntpd timekeeping daemon. The default NetBSD
    installation is not affected, but those who run the daemon under
    customised user id's should take care to read the advisory.
   </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SA2005-012.txt.asc">SA2005-012</ulink>
    describes a denial-of-service kernel crash that may be initiated
    by unprivileged users, but only for kernels with optional
    DIAGNOSTIC kernel assertions enabled.  Some kernels shipped in
    releases include this option.
   </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SA2005-013.txt.asc">SA2005-013</ulink>
    describes a potential privilege escalation attack against certain
    set-uid or set-gid programs that call exec. All kernels are affected,
    and must be upgraded to close the vulnerability.
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
  All users of older versions are encouraged to upgrade to NetBSD 2.1
  to collect the fixes for all known security issues prior to
  these. The forthcoming NetBSD 2.1.1 update will include the fixes
  for these remaining issues, which are available in source form from
  CVS now.  Users tracking -current and 3.0_BETA are also encouraged
  to upgrade in accordance with these advisories.
</para>
<para>
  Please check the <ulink url="../support/security/advisory.html">Security
  Advisories</ulink> page for full details of all advisories.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="newdev200511">
<title>01 Nov 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developer:
</para>
<para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    &a.jld; (login: jld),
    who will be working on port-xen.
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-oct-2005">
<title>01 Nov 2005 - Changes to the Packages Collection in October 2005</title>
<para>&a.agc; has posted his monthly account of the
changes to the Packages Collection in October 2005.  By his
calculations, at the end of October 2005, there were 5657 packages
in the Packages Collection, up from 5558 the previous month, a rise
of 99.</para>
<para>The Package of the Month award (jointly) goes to:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
  <filename role="pkg">graphics/digikam</filename>, nominated by
  Simon Burge, who uses it to tag and organise photos really easily.
  Apparently Simon has more than 3000 photos, and with a click or
  two he can select really easily after they have been tagged.
  Simon also nominated:
</listitem><listitem>
  <filename role="pkg">sysutils/rsnapshot</filename> for backing
  up a large amount of data, a perl utility on the server, and
  rsync on the clients to be backed up.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Please read Alistair G. Crooks's <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/11/01/0001.html">message</ulink>
for details.</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="200510">
<title>October 2005</title>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-sep-2005">
<title>22 Oct 2005 - Changes to the Packages Collection in September 2005</title>
<para>
At the end of September 2005, there were 5558 packages in the <ulink
url="../docs/software/packages.html">Packages Collection</ulink>.
Please read &a.agc;'s <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-users/2005/10/22/0003.html">message</ulink>
to learn more details about the changes to the Packages Collection, including
notable additions, updates and choosing the Package of the Month September:
<filename role="pkg">archivers/rzip</filename>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="release-timelines-october-2005">
<title>21 Oct 2005 - New timelines for upcoming NetBSD 3.0</title>
<para>
&a.tron; of the NetBSD Release Engineering team announced an update to the
estimated timeframe for the upcoming release of NetBSD 3.0. NetBSD 3.0 is
planned to be released in the second half of November 2005. As usual,
this date is still subject to change.  
</para>
<para>
More details about the release schedule can be found in &a.tron;'s <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/10/21/0000.html">message</ulink>
to the <ulink url="../mailinglists/#netbsd-announce">netbsd-announce</ulink>
mailing list.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="soc-summary05">
<title>16 Oct 2005 - Summer of Code Summary</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Project is pleased to announce the results of its participation in
Google's Open Source program, the <quote>Summer of Code</quote>.   After
several weeks of hard work, all participating projects have been completed in
time and according to the set goals and have subsequently been rated a
success.  For more details, please refer to the <ulink
url="../foundation/press/soc-summary.html">press release</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200510">
<title>01 Oct 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      &a.apb; (login: apb),
      who will be working on the building process and syspkgs.
    </listitem>    <listitem>
      &a.joerg; (login: joerg),
      who will be working on the NetBSD Packages Collection.
    </listitem>  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="200509">
<title>September 2005</title>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-2005Q3">
<title>26 Sep 2005 - pkgsrc-2005Q3 has been branched</title>
<para>The pkgsrc developers are very proud to announce the new
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal> branch, which has support for more packages than
previous branches (5551 packages supported on 13 platforms).  As
well as updated versions of many packages, the infrastructure of
pkgsrc itself has been improved for better platform and compiler
support, and also for enhanced security.  At the same time, the
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q2</literal> branch has been deprecated, and continuing engineering
starts on the <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal> branch.</para>
<para>We would also like to thank the Dragonfly BSD project for
adopting pkgsrc as their packaging system - this is the first pkgsrc
branch since that announcement, and we have brought on board some
Dragonfly developers specifically to look after issues related to
that platform.</para>
<para>The source tar files for the new branch can be found at:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/2005Q3/pkgsrc-2005Q3.tar.gz"/></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/2005Q3/pkgsrc-2005Q3.tar.bz2"/></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>And of course, you can also use the <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal>
tag to check it out yourself from anoncvs.NetBSD.org or any of the
<ulink url="../mirrors/#anoncvs">mirrors</ulink>.</para>
<para>Please see the detailed <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal> announcement in
<ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/09/26/0000.html">&a.agc;'s email</ulink> to the netbsd-announce mailing list.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd21-rc5">
<title>25 Sep 2005 - NetBSD 2.1 RC5 available</title>
<para>The NetBSD Release Engineering team has announced that NetBSD
2.1 RC5 is available for testing. (A security issue came up shortly
after RC4 was tagged, so it was never announced).</para>
<para>NetBSD 2.1 RC5 is available in the <quote>daily builds</quote>
section of The NetBSD Project's FTP site -
ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD-daily/netbsd-2-1-RC5/
(please use <ulink url="../mirrors/#ftp">mirrors</ulink> if
possible).</para>
<para>We anticipate that this will be the final release candidate
for NetBSD 2.1, barring any major issues or security problems, so
we also highly encourage you to test it out and report any bugs
using &man.send-pr.1; utility.</para>
<para>For more information see <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/09/25/0000.html">&a.riz;'s email</ulink> to the netbsd-announce mailing list.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="tmpfs">
<title>10 Sep 2005 - file system tmpfs added to NetBSD</title>
<para>&a.jmmv; has added the result of his summer project, a new memory-based
file system written as a part of <ulink
url="#soc0605">Google's Summer of Code</ulink> (SoC) campaign, to the NetBSD
source tree. A detailed description how to use the new file system
can be found in &a.jmmv;'s <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-kern/2005/09/10/0004.html">message</ulink>
to the mailing list <ulink url="../mailinglists/#tech-kern">tech-kern</ulink>.
</para>
<para>A report about the <ulink
url="http://netbsd-soc.sourceforge.net/">SoC projects related to NetBSD</ulink>
will probably be released in October.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-freeze-2005Q3-announced">
<title>08 Sep 2005 - pkgsrc tree frozen for pkgsrc-2005Q3</title>
<para>
Today, &a.agc; announced in a <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/09/08/0040.html">message</ulink>
to the <ulink url="../mailinglists/#tech-pkg">tech-pkg mailing list</ulink>
that the NetBSD Packages Team has frozen the development of new features
for pkgsrc to prepare for the release of the next stable branch
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q3</literal>. The freeze period has begun September
8th 2005 and is expected to last two weeks.
During this period, the developers will bring down the number of open
problem reports and fix problems shown by the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/pkgsrc-bulk/">bulk builds</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd21-rc3">
<title>07 Sep 2005 - NetBSD 2.1 RC3 available</title>
<para>The NetBSD Release Engineering team has announced that the
release process of NetBSD 2.1 has begun. NetBSD 2.1 RC3 builds are
available at ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD-daily/netbsd-2-1-RC3.
NetBSD 2.1 RC1 and RC2 were not announced publicly because of build
problems on some supported platforms.</para>
<para>For more information see <ulink url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/09/07/0000.html">&a.riz;'s</ulink> email to the netbsd-announce
mailing list.</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="200508">
<title>August 2005</title>
<sect3 id="pkgsrc-dflybsd">
<title>31 Aug 2005 - pkgsrc will be part of DragonFly</title>
<para>
Matthew Dillon, DragonFlyBSD founder and chief developer,  <ulink
url="http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/users/2005-08/msg00347.html">announced</ulink>
that pkgsrc will be the official packaging system in DragonFlyBSD
starting with the next release, scheduled for December 2005.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="release-timelines-august-2005">
<title>23 Aug 2005 - New timelines for upcoming releases</title>
<para>
&a.tron; of the NetBSD Release Engineering team announced an update to the
prospective timeframes for upcoming NetBSD releases. NetBSD 3.0 is planned for
an October 2005 release; NetBSD 2.1 for the middle of September 2005.  As
usual, these dates are of course subject to change.
</para>
<para>
For more information, read the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/08/22/0000.html">announcement
in the mailing list archives</ulink> and see the release engineering websites
for the <ulink url="../releng/releng-2.html">NetBSD 2</ulink> and 
<ulink url="../releng/releng-3.html">NetBSD 3</ulink> branches.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="toaster">
<title>11 Aug 2005 - NetBSD ported to working toaster</title>
<para>It has long been regarded that the UNIX-like OS NetBSD is portable
to every type of machine except perhaps your kitchen toaster.
<ulink url="http://www.embeddedarm.com/">Technologic Systems</ulink>,
however, has conquered this last frontier. Using one of its rugged embedded
TS-7200 single-board computers housed inside the empty space of a standard 2
slice toaster, Technologic Systems has designed a functional
<ulink url="http://www.embeddedarm.com/news/netbsd_toaster.htm">NetBSD
controlled toaster</ulink>.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newcore200508">
<title>03 Aug 2005 - New NetBSD Core Team</title>
<para>The NetBSD core team has been working together for two years in its
present form, and, such are the stresses of the job, some changes have
become necessary.  We'd like to thank the members of the core team who
have spent a lot of time and effort looking after the technical
direction of the NetBSD project, and steering it to where it is
today.</para>
<para>Please see &a.agc;'s <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/08/03/0000.html">email</ulink> to
<email>netbsd-announce@NetBSD.org</email> for more information.</para>

<para>The new NetBSD Core Team is listed at the corresponding <ulink
  url="/people/core.html">group page</ulink>.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200508">
<title>01 Aug 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      &a.tonio; (login: tonio),
      who will be working on the NetBSD Packages Collection.
    </listitem>    <listitem>
      &a.hiramatsu; (login: hiramatsu),
      who will be working on the NetBSD Packages Collection.
    </listitem>    <listitem>
      sam (login: sam),
      who will be working on ath and net80211.
    </listitem>  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="200507">
<title>July 2005</title>

<sect3 id="donations-status">
<title>19 Jul 2005 - Call for donations -- status</title>
<para>
The NetBSD project would like to thank all contributors for their generous 
response to the <ulink url="#pledge0605">recent call for donations</ulink>.
In only one month, almost US $27K was <ulink 
url="../donations/">donated</ulink> allowing the NetBSD Foundation to purchase 
five new machines; three of those machines will be added to the nightly build
infrastructure and two of those machines will become anonymous cvs 
servers.
</para>
<para>For more information, including the detailed specifications of the
hardware purchased, please see <ulink 
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/07/19/0000.html">&a.christos; email to the netbsd-announce mailing list</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
If you would like to join the number of donors and make a donation
(tax-deductible in the US) using your credit card or PayPal account,
please click on one of the buttons below or contact 
<email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email> to make other arrangements.
<html:form action="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr"
  method="post" style="text-align: center;">
  <html:input type="hidden" name="cmd" value="_xclick"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="business" value="paypal@NetBSD.org"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="item_name" value="The NetBSD Foundation"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="no_shipping" value="1"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="return" value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="cancel_return"
    value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
  <html:input type="image" src="/images/links/paypal.gif" name="submit"
    alt="Donate using PayPal"/>
  <html:input type="image" src="/images/links/paypal-cc.gif" name="submit"
    alt="Donate using PayPal"/> 
</html:form>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="report2005q2">
<title>12 Jul 2005 - Second Quarterly Status Report in 2005 published</title>
<para>
&a.jschauma; published the NetBSD Foundation's second quarterly status report
in 2005, covering the months April through June of 2005.  Among many other
things, this status report covers NetBSD's participation in Google's
<quote>Summer of Code</quote>, the new stable pkgsrc branch and various
port-specific items.  It is available online at <ulink
url="../foundation/reports/2005Q2.html">http://www.NetBSD.org/foundation/reports/2005Q2.html</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="sec-note-200507">
<title>08 Jul 2005 - New Security Note released</title>
<para>The NetBSD Security Note <ulink 
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SN20050708-1.txt.asc">20050708-1</ulink>
  regarding to the recent zlib buffer overflow has been released.
  The zlib in the NetBSD base system is <emphasis
  role="bold">not</emphasis> vulnerable, but pkgsrc 
  had a vulnerable version.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200507">
<title>01 Jul 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    &a.rpaulo; (login: rpaulo),
    who will be working on NetBSD guide and website documentation.
    </listitem>    
    <listitem>
    &a.mishka; (login: mishka),
    who will be working on russian translation and advocacy.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    &a.gdt; (login: gdt),
    who will be working on the NetBSD Packages Collection, networking code and the building process.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    &a.silke; (login: silke),
    who will be working with admins.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pf-3.7">
<title>01 Jul 2005 - pf from OpenBSD 3.7 updated on -current</title>

<para>&a.peter; updated &man.pf.4; from OpenBSD 3.7 adding new
features and bugfixes. For a list of changes <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/07/01/0003.html">see his
email to -current users mailing list</ulink>.</para>
<para>If you notice any problem please use the &man.send-pr.1; tool to
send a problem report.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="sa-050701">
<title>01 Jul 2005 - Two New Security Advisories released</title>

<para>NetBSD Security Advisories <ulink
    url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SA2005-001.txt.asc">SA2005-001</ulink>
    concerning to HyperThreaded CPUs and <ulink
    url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/advisories/NetBSD-SA2005-002.txt.asc">SA2005-002</ulink>
    concerning to a local DoS via audio device have been released. 
    More details, including information on solutions 
    and workarounds, are located in each individual security advisory.</para>
<para>More information on previous <ulink
  url="../support/security/advisory.html">Security Advisories</ulink> is
  available in the <ulink url="../support/security/">NetBSD Security</ulink> 
  pages.</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="200506">
<title>June 2005</title>

<sect3 id="soc0605">
<title>26 Jun 2005 - Announcing NetBSD and the Google <quote>Summer of Code</quote> Projects</title>
<para>
When Google announced the <quote>Summer of Code</quote>, its program designed to
introduce students to the world of open source software development,
the NetBSD Project understood the value of this project and entered as
a mentoring organization. Over a period of two weeks, students
researched the list of possible projects and discussed their proposals
on the public mailing lists and in private with developers and other
users alike. After evaluating over 100 distinct applications, the
NetBSD Foundation is now pleased to announce the list of projects that
have been chosen. See the associated
<ulink url="../foundation/press/soc.html">press release</ulink>
for all the details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pledge0605">
<title>12 Jun 2005 - Help NetBSD help you!</title>
<para>
In the past, NetBSD has been hesitant to appeal directly to its users for
financial support.  However, we have relied for too long on the generosity of
a small number of regular donors.  We can greatly improve the services we
provide to all NetBSD users with your financial help.  Please see <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-advocacy/2005/06/12/0002.html">&a.tls;'s
call for donations</ulink> for more details.  You can make a direct donation
using your credit card or PayPal account (click on the button below)
or contact
<email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email> to make other arrangements.
Donations are tax-deductible in the Unites States. Many thanks in advance!
</para>
<html:form action="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr" 
  method="post" style="text-align: center;">
  <html:input type="hidden" name="cmd" value="_xclick"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="business" value="paypal@NetBSD.org"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="item_name" value="The NetBSD Foundation"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="no_shipping" value="1"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="return" value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
  <html:input type="hidden" name="cancel_return" 
    value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
  <html:input type="image" src="/images/links/paypal.gif" name="submit" 
    alt="Donate using PayPal"/>
  <html:input type="image" src="/images/links/paypal-cc.gif" name="submit"
    alt="Donate using PayPal"/>
</html:form>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-freeze-2005Q2-announced">
<title>02 Jun 2005 - pkgsrc will freeze for pkgsrc-2005Q2</title>
<para>
&a.agc; <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/06/01/0045.html">announced</ulink> yesterday that the NetBSD Packages Team will freeze the
development of new features for pkgsrc to prepare for the release of the next
stable branch <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q2</literal>. The freeze period will begin
on June 6th 2005 and is expected to last two weeks at the most. During this
time, the developers will bring down the PR count and fix problems shown
by the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/pkgsrc-bulk/">bulk builds</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="summerofcode">
<title>02 Jun 2005 - Summer of Code</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Project is pleased to participate in Google's <ulink
url="http://code.google.com/summerofcode.html">Summer of Code</ulink> as a
mentoring organization.  A list of possible projects is available from <ulink
url="../contrib/projects.html">this page</ulink>.  If you are interested in
any of these projects or have other suggestions, please contact &a.jschauma;
<email>jschauma</email> or post to the relevant lists suggested on the
projects page.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200506">
<title>01 Jun 2005 - New Developer</title>
<para> 
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developer:
</para>
<para> 
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      &a.macallan; (login: macallan) will be working on the macppc port,
      the sparc64 port, the sparc port and xsrc.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="may-2005">
<title>May 2005</title>

<sect3 id="downtime-ftp_fi_netbsd_org-20050601">
<title>31 May 2005 - Downtime for ftp.fi.NetBSD.org</title>
<para>
Due to a relocation of the server hardware, <systemitem
class="fqdomainname">ftp.fi.NetBSD.org</systemitem> will be
down on June 1st, 2005, and possibly on June 2nd, 2005, depending
on how well the move goes.  Hosting for <systemitem
class="fqdomainname">ftp.fi.NetBSD.org</systemitem> is
kindly provided by the Finnish University and Research Network (<ulink
url="http://www.funet.fi">FUNET</ulink>).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrccon05-slides">
<title>29 May 2005 - pkgsrcCon 2005 presentations online</title>
<para>
Most of the presentations given at this year's <ulink
url="http://www.pkgsrccon.org">pkgsrcCon</ulink> are now available <ulink
url="http://www.pkgsrccon.org/2005/presentations.html">online</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="rasvpn-docs">
<title>25 May 2005 - Remote User Access VPN Documentation</title>
<para>
&a.manu; recently added <ulink
url="../docs/network/ipsec/rasvpn.html">detailed
documentation</ulink> on how to set up a Remote User Access VPN under NetBSD.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="anoncvs-down-20050521">
<title>21 May 2005 - AnonCVS outage</title>
<para>
The anonymous CVS server will be unavailable for much of May 21
2005, while we rework and simplify its configuration.  Among other less
immediately obvious benefits we hope this will allow us to begin offering
anonymous CVS access over IPv6.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="donation-sun">
<title>09 May 2005 - Sun Hardware Donation for pkgsrc work</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Foundation is pleased to announce the generous donation of
two machines from <ulink url="http://www.sun.com/">Sun Microsystems</ulink>
for the purpose of advancing the
development of The NetBSD Packages Collection under Solaris.
</para>
<para>
<quote>Sun is looking forward to working with the NetBSD Project, and
certainly wants to support the pkgsrc efforts,</quote> commented
Alan DuBoff, a member of Solaris Engineering at Sun.
</para>
<para>
For more information, read the
<ulink url="../foundation/press/sun-donation.html">press release here</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-mar-2005">
<title>09 May 2005 - Changes to the Packages Collection in March 2005</title>
<para>
At the end of March 2005, there were 5377 packages in the Packages
Collection.  Please read &a.agc;' email in the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-users/2005/05/08/0005.html">mailing
list archives</ulink> to read about the changes to the Packages Collection
in March 2005, including notable additions, notable updates, and choosing
the Package of the Month.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="release-timelines-may-2005">
<title>02 May 2005 - Prospective timelines for upcoming releases</title>
<para>
The release engineers announced the prospective timeframes for upcoming
NetBSD releases. NetBSD 3.0 is planned for a late July 2005 release;
NetBSD 2.1 planned for a late June 2005 release; and
NetBSD 1.6.3 is planned for an August or September 2005 release.
</para>
<para>
For more information, read the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/05/02/0002.html">announcement
in the mailing list archives</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
When 2.1 is released, <literal>netbsd-2-0</literal> will be shutdown. Possibly a
2.0.3 update may be done before then.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="daily-builds-may-2005">
<title>02 May 2005 - Daily builds available for public again</title>
<para>
&a.jmc; announced that the
regular daily builds for NetBSD have begun again and are available for
public consumption at
ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD-daily/.
See the announcement in the <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/05/02/0001.html">netbsd-announce
mailing list archives</ulink> for more information.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="cvsweb-downtime-may-2005">
<title>02 May 2005 - Software maintenance for <systemitem
class="fqdomainname">cvsweb.NetBSD.org</systemitem></title>
<para>
This week, <ulink url="http://cvsweb.NetBSD.org/"><systemitem
class="fqdomainname">cvsweb.NetBSD.org</systemitem></ulink>
(<systemitem class="fqdomainname">pigu.iri.co.jp</systemitem>) will be down
at times for software maintenance.
You are welcome to use one of the
<ulink url="../mirrors/#cvsweb">cvsweb mirrors</ulink> during the
outage.
</para>
<para>
This also affects the Japanese mailing lists (@<systemitem
class="domainname">jp.NetBSD.org</systemitem>) and the
following Japanese mirror services
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">cvsup.jp.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">cvsweb.jp.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">www.jp.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200505">
<title>01 May 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      &a.seanb; (login: seanb)
       will be working on kernel, utilities, libc and networking.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      &a.elad; (login: elad)
      will be working on veriexec, kernel and security.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="april-2005">
<title>April 2005</title>

<sect3 id="downtime-www2_be_NetBSD_org">
<title>28 Apr 2005 - Belgian NetBSD mirrors out of service (updated)</title>
<para>
Due to hardware failure, the following mirror servers
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">anoncvs.be.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">cvsweb.be.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">ftp.be.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">www2.be.NetBSD.org</systemitem>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
are unavailable at the moment.
</para>

<para>
As it is not clear at this time how long the downtime will be, please
use one of the nearby European 
<ulink url="../mirrors/">mirrors</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
<note>Since 2005-05-09 the Belgian mirrors are online again.
</note>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="netbsd-2.0.2">
<title>14 Apr 2005 - NetBSD 2.0.2 released</title>
<para>
&a.jmc; has announced that update 2.0.2 of the NetBSD     
operating system is now available.  NetBSD 2.0.2 is the second
security/critical update of the NetBSD 2.0 release   
branch. This represents a selected subset of fixes deemed critical in nature
for stability or security reasons.  More details are available in the <ulink
url="../releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.0.2.html">NetBSD 2.0.2 Release
Announcement</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="report2005q1">
<title>08 Apr 2005 - First Quarterly Status Report in 2005 published</title>
<para>
&a.jschauma; published the NetBSD Foundation's first quarterly status report
in 2005, covering the months January through March of 2005.  Among many other
things, this status report covers the addition of TCP/SACK and PAM support,
the opening of the Foundations Online Store, the new stable pkgsrc branch and
various port-specific items.  It is available online at <ulink
url="../foundation/reports/2005Q1.html">http://www.NetBSD.org/foundation/reports/2005Q1.html</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="pkgs-2005Q1">
<title>06 Apr 2005 - Binary packages for 2005Q1 available</title>
<para>
&a.hubertf; has uploaded a total of about 10GB of binary packages built
for NetBSD 2.0/i386 and NetBSD 1.6.2/i386 from the
<ulink url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/03/24/0025.html">
<literal>pkgsrc-2005Q1</literal> branch</ulink> to ftp.NetBSD.org. To install the binaries,
set your PKG_PATH for pkg_add as follows:
</para> 
<para> 
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>for NetBSD 2.0:
      <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/pkgsrc-2005Q1/NetBSD-2.0/i386/All"/>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>for NetBSD 1.6.2:
 	<ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/pkgsrc-2005Q1/NetBSD-1.6.2/i386/All"/>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
Some of the highlights:
  <itemizedlist>
 	<listitem>apache-2.0.53</listitem>
 	<listitem>gnome-2.8.3</listitem>
 	<listitem>mysql-4.1.10a</listitem>
 	<listitem>openldap-2.2.20</listitem>
 	<listitem>openoffice-1.1.4</listitem>
 	<listitem>perl-5.8.6</listitem>
 	<listitem>postgresql-8.0.1</listitem>
 	<listitem>ruby-1.8.2</listitem>
 	<listitem>xentools-2.0.3</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Updated 2005-04-09</emphasis>: &a.jschauma; uploaded binary packages for
NetBSD-2.0/amd64 and IRIX64-6.5, and &a.bouyer; uploaded binary packages for
NetBSD-2.0/sparc, all including PGP signed checksum files to:
</para>
<para> 
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>NetBSD-2.0/amd64:
      <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/pkgsrc-2005Q1/NetBSD-2.0/amd64/"/>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>NetBSD-2.0/sparc:
      <ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/pkgsrc-2005Q1/NetBSD-2.0/sparc/"/>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>IRIX64-6.5:
 	<ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/packages/IRIX-6.5/64/pkgsrc-2005Q1/"/>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ipsec-tools">
<title>04 Apr 2005 - ipsec-tools included with NetBSD</title>
<para>
&a.manu; has been working on integrating NAT Traversal and
recently replaced the KAME based racoon in NetBSD with the
feature-enhanced <quote><ulink
url="http://ipsec-tools.sf.net/">ipsec-tools</ulink></quote> version.
NetBSD can now be setup to replace Cisco 3000 VPN concentrators,
while Cisco VPN clients can still be used, talking to NetBSD instead.
</para>
<para>
Many more changes come with the ipsec-tools, including dead peer
detection, privilege separation, IKE mode config, IKE and ESP
fragmentation, configurable path to certificate authority, and hook
scripts. <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/02/19/0013.html">See
&a.manu;' mail in the current-users mailing list archives</ulink>
for a more complete list.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ipf4.1.8">
<title>04 Apr 2005 - IP Filter upgraded to 4.1.8 on -current</title>
<para>
 &a.martti; upgraded IPFilter to the latest version (4.1.8) on
 NetBSD -current. For information about the changes, and recompiling
 the kernel and the ipf tools <ulink
 url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/04/03/0003.html">see
 the email in the current-users mailing list archives</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200504">
<title>01 Apr 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      &a.mlelstv; (login: mlelstv),
      who will be working on IEEE 1394 and miscellaneous tasks.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      &a.riz; (login: riz),
      who will be working on the NetBSD Packages Collection, port-i386 and
      networking.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      &a.kurahone; (login: kurahone),
      who will be working on TCP/IP stack, scalability and performance and ACPI.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="march-2005">
<title>March 2005</title>

<sect3 id="gnome_2_10_0">
<title>31 Mar 2005 - GNOME 2.10.0 available in pkgsrc</title>
<para>
&a.jmmv; <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/03/22/0014.html">finished</ulink>
updating the GNOME packages in pkgsrc-current to 2.10.0, the latest
stable version. Around 80 packages have been updated and some new ones
have been added.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-2005Q1">
<title>24 Mar 2005 - pkgsrc branch 2005Q1 created</title>
<para>
  &a.agc; <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/03/24/0025.html">announced</ulink> the availability of the new stable branch
  <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q1</literal> of the <ulink
url="../docs/pkgsrc/">NetBSD Packages Collection</ulink>. The
  former branch <literal>pkgsrc-2004Q4</literal> is now deprecated.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="bouyer-xen2-merged">
<title>10 Mar 2005 - bouyer-xen2 merged into HEAD</title>
<para>
&a.bouyer; has merged the <literal>bouyer-xen2</literal> branch into
NetBSD-current.  This means that support for Xen 2.0 (both in privileged and
unprivileged mode) will be part of NetBSD 3.0.  See <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/port-xen/2005/03/09/0000.html">Manuel's
email to the port-xen mailing list</ulink> for details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-frozen-q1">
<title>07 Mar 2005 - pkgsrc now frozen</title>
<para>
The <ulink url="../docs/pkgsrc/">NetBSD Packages Collection</ulink>
is now frozen for a duration of 2 weeks in preparation of the first stable
branch in 2005, <literal>pkgsrc-2005Q1</literal>.  During this time, no new packages
will be imported in pkgsrc, and the NetBSD Packages team will focus on fixing
open PRs and stabilizing the infrastructure.
</para>
<para>
Please see <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/03/07/0026.html">Alistair
Crooks's announcement</ulink> on the tech-pkg mailing list.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-changes-february05">
<title>07 Mar 2005 - Changes to pkgsrc in February 05</title>
<para>
&a.agc; has posted his monthly account of the changes to the Packages
Collection in February 2005 to the tech-pkg mailing list.  According to
Alistair, there were 5377 packages in the NetBSD Packages Collection, up from
5331 the previous month, a rise of 47 with many notable updates as well.  An
important change in the pkgsrc infrastructure was made due to the recent
announcement that collisions have been found in SHA1:  pkgsrc now supports
multiple digest algorithms and distpatches and all the distinfo files in
pkgsrc have been updated, where possible, to use multiple checksums.  More
details, including the Package of the Month Award, can be found in <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/03/07/0023.html">Alistair's
email</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="press-xen">
<title>04 Mar 2005 - NetBSD and Xen</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Foundation has published a <ulink
url="../foundation/press/xen.html">press release</ulink> reporting on the benefits
of the <ulink url="../ports/xen/">NetBSD/xen port</ulink>, initially committed
by &a.cl; as <ulink url="2004.html#newportxen">previously reported</ulink>.  Since
then, much progress has been made, and the NetBSD Project is now using NetBSD/xen
internally.  See <ulink url="../foundation/press/xen.html">the press
release</ulink> for further details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200503">
<title>01 Mar 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
</para>
<para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
	&a.kiyohara; (login: kiyohara), who will be working on ieee1394 
	and OpenBlockS266 (evbppc).</listitem>
    <listitem>
	&a.rillig; (login: rillig), who will be working on the NetBSD 
	Packages Collection.</listitem>
    <listitem>
	&a.schwarz; (login: schwarz), who will be working on the 
	NetBSD Packages Collection.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="february-2005">
<title>February 2005</title>

<sect3 id="pam-enabled-0205">
<title>27 Feb 2005 - PAM enabled on HEAD</title>
<para>
&a.christos; announced today that most programs that perform authentication
will be using PAM, including &man.login.1;, &man.su.1;, &man.xdm.1;,
&man.ftpd.8;, &man.telnetd.8;, ppp, and others.  Please see his <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/02/27/0005.html">email to
the current-users mailing list</ulink> for details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="2.0interviews">
<title>27 Feb 2005 - NetBSD 2.0 interviews</title>
<para>
Shortly after <ulink
url="../releases/formal-2.0/NetBSD-2.0.html">NetBSD 2.0</ulink> was released,
<ulink url="http://www.newsforge.com">Newsforge</ulink> ran <ulink
url="http://trends.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=04/12/22/1954233">this
article</ulink> entitled <quote>Understanding NetBSD 2.0's new technology</quote>, which
included an interview with a number of NetBSD developers.  Now, several weeks
after this article, the author Federico Biancuzzi has <ulink
url="http://www.onlamp.com/lpt/a/5638">published his follow-up
interview</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="em64t">
<title>20 Feb 2005 - NetBSD/amd64 running on Intel EM64T</title>
<para>
Release 2.0 of <ulink url="../ports/amd64/">NetBSD/amd64</ulink> has been
<ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/port-amd64/2005/02/20/0001.html">confirmed</ulink>
to run successfully on Intel x86 CPUs with 64-bit extension <ulink
url="http://developer.intel.com/technology/64bitextensions/">EM64T</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ipf4.1.6">
<title>20 Feb 2005 - ipf 4.1.6 imported</title>
<para>
IPFilter in NetBSD-current has been updated to the latest version
(4.1.6). You must recompile your kernel and the ipf tools to use the new
version.  See <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/02/19/0014.html">&a.martti;'s
email</ulink> to the current-users mailing list for more details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="cvsweb-service-time">
<title>19 Feb 2005 - Maintenance period for cvsweb.NetBSD.org</title>
<para>
<ulink url="http://cvsweb.NetBSD.org/">cvsweb.NetBSD.org</ulink>
(pigu.iri.co.jp) will be down from Sat Feb 19 13:00 GMT to Mon Feb 21
00:30 GMT due to a shutdown of power for building maintenance. You are
welcome to use one of the
<ulink url="../mirrors/#cvsweb">cvsweb mirrors</ulink> during this
outage.
</para>
<para>
This also affects the Japanese mailing lists (@jp.NetBSD.org) and the
following Japanese mirror services
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>anoncvs.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>cvsup.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>cvsweb.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>iso.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>rsync.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>sup.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
  <listitem>www.jp.NetBSD.org</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="jp-ftp-mirror-down">
<title>15 Feb 2005 - Japanese FTP mirror out of service</title>
<para>
The Japanese mirror <ulink url="ftp://ftp.jp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/">ftp.jp.NetBSD.org</ulink>,
operated by the <ulink url="http://www.jp.NetBSD.org/ja/JP/">Japanese
NetBSD users group</ulink>, is out of service at the moment due to
broken harddisks. It is expected to be available again in early March. In
the meantime you can use one of the other <ulink url="../mirrors/index.html#ftp">NetBSD mirrors</ulink>
in Japan.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc-changes-january05">
<title>09 Feb 2005 - Changes to pkgsrc in January 05</title>
<para>
&a.agc; has posted his monthly account of the changes to the Packages
Collection in January 2005 to the tech-pkg mailing list.  According to
Alistair, there were 5331 packages in the NetBSD Packages Collection, up from
5266 the previous month, a rise of 65 with many notable updates as well.  More
details, including the Package of the Month Award, can be found in <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-pkg/2005/02/09/0008.html">his
email</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ipf4.1.5">
<title>08 Feb 2005 - ipf 4.1.5 imported</title>
<para>
&a.martti; announced today that he upgraded IPFilter to the latest version
(4.1.5) on NetBSD -current. You must recompile kernel and the ipf tools to use
the new version.  See <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/02/08/0007.html">Martti's
email</ulink> to the current-users mailing list for more details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="tnf-report04">
<title>04 Feb 2005 - The Annual NetBSD Status Report</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Foundation held its annual meeting, during which the developers
discussed, among other things, how NetBSD progressed over the last year
and what is planned for the coming year. The <ulink
url="../foundation/reports/2004.html">Annual NetBSD Status Report</ulink>
summarizes the meeting.
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="january-2005">
<title>January 2005</title>

<sect3 id="cafepress">
<title>28 Jan 2005 - NetBSD online store</title>
<para>
&a.reed; of the NetBSD Communication Executive Committee <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/01/28/0000.html">announced</ulink>
that NetBSD now has an online store selling various products to help raise
funds at <ulink url="http://www.cafepress.com/NetBSD/"/>.  Items currently on
sale include shirts, sweatshirts, a mug, wall clock, mousepad,
logo magnets, and tote bags.
</para>
<para>
All profits from this online store will be used to directly fund NetBSD,
such as hardware, promotion, legal and accounting fees, and other
expenses.
</para>
<para>
Please visit <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/donations/"/> for more
information on how to donate to the non-profit NetBSD project.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="EOL-1.5">
<title>26 Jan 2005 - NetBSD 1.5 EOLed</title>
<para>
&a.jmc; of the NetBSD Release Engineering team <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/01/26/0000.html">announced</ulink>
that, in keeping with NetBSD's policy of maintaining only the current (2.0)
and most recent (1.6) release branches, the release of NetBSD 2.0 marks the
end-of-life for NetBSD 1.5.  This means that the netbsd-1-5 branch will no
longer be actively maintained.
</para>
<para>
There will be no more pullups to the branch (even for security issues).
There will be no security advisories made for 1.5.
And the 1.5 releases on ftp.NetBSD.org have been moved to
<filename>/pub/NetBSD/NetBSD-archive</filename>.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="anoncvs-back">
<title>14 Jan 2005 - anoncvs back online</title>
<para>
As <ulink url="2004.html#anoncvs-down">reported earlier</ulink>, the project's anoncvs
server suffered from some hardware failure and had to be taken out of service
temporarily.  &a.christos; announced today on behalf of the NetBSD Systems
Administration Executive Committee that anoncvs.NetBSD.org is now back in
service, after the hard work of &a.spz;, &a.gendalia;, &a.thorpej; and &a.tls;.
</para>
<para>
For more details refer to <ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/01/14/0020.html">&a.christos;' message</ulink> to the current-users
mailing list, in which he reminds users of the opportunity to <ulink
url="../donations/">donate</ulink> to the project to help improve the
reliability of our services.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="branches-explained">
<title>13 Jan 2005 - NetBSD branches explained</title>
<para>
James Chacon of the NetBSD release engineering team explains the NetBSD
naming scheme to explain future releases and upcoming changes.  Please see
<ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/netbsd-announce/2005/01/13/0000.html">his
message to netbsd-announce</ulink> for details.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="pkgsrc2004q4-packages">
<title>12 Jan 2005 - Binary packages from pkgsrc-2004Q4 available</title>
<para>
After the <ulink url="2004.html#pkgsrc-2004Q4">last stable pkgsrc branch</ulink> was
cut, many developers started off their bulk-builds to provide binary packages
from this branch.  The first results are now available (as posted to our
<ulink
url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/pkgsrc-bulk/2005/01/">pkgsrc-bulk</ulink>
mailing list), and binary packages have been uploaded to the <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/">ftp server</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
The binary packages available so far are: <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/1.6.2/m68k-softfloat/">NetBSD-1.6.2/m68k</ulink>
(softfloat), <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/powerpc/">NetBSD-2.0/powerpc</ulink>
and <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/vax/">NetBSD-2.0/vax</ulink>
(uploaded by &a.jklos;), <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/mipseb/">the NetBSD-2.0
mipseb ports</ulink> (<ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/evbmips/">evbmips</ulink>,
<ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/mipsco/">mipsco</ulink>,
<ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/newsmips/">newsmips</ulink>,
<ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/sbmips/">sbmips</ulink>, and
<ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/sgimips/">sgimips</ulink>)
and <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/sparc/">NetBSD-2.0/sparc</ulink>
(uploaded by &a.jschauma;&mdash;PGP signed checksums are available for these
files in the respective directories) and of course the <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/1.6.2/i386/">NetBSD-1.6.2/i386</ulink>
and <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/packages/2.0/i386/">NetBSD-2.0/i386</ulink>
ports (uploaded by &a.hubertf;).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="report2004q4">
<title>11 Jan 2005 - Fourth Quarterly Status Report published</title>
<para>
&a.jschauma; published the NetBSD Foundation's fourth quarterly status report,
covering the months October through December of 2004.  Among many other
things, this status report covers the publication of the new NetBSD Logo, the
new pkgsrc branch, the new NetBSD/iyonix port and of course the release of
NetBSD 2.0.  It is available online at <ulink
url="../foundation/reports/2004Q4.html">http://www.NetBSD.org/foundation/reports/2004Q4.html</ulink>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="donation-intel">
<title>11 Jan 2005 - Intel donates hardware to the NetBSD Project</title>

<para>
    The NetBSD project would like to express its gratitude for the
    fact that the department of application engineering at Intel, who
    provide design-in support for the XScale based I/O processors, has
    donated hardware to the NetBSD project.
</para>

<para>
    Two Xscale boards (IOP321, IOP315) have been donated to a
    developer of the NetBSD project. The boards will be used for
    maintenance and development of the NetBSD/ARM port, as well as
    enhancing and completing the support for Thumb code on
    NetBSD. Furthermore, the boards will also serve for testing and
    developing the GCC compiler used by the NetBSD operating system.
</para>

<para>
    As a non-profit, volunteer organisation with no commercial
    backing, the NetBSD Project depends on support from individuals
    and companies to continue development of the world's most portable
    operating system and packages system. Due to its 501(c)(3)
    status, monetary donations are fully tax deductible. Information
    on supporting the NetBSD project via money or hardware can be
    found at <ulink
    url="http://www.NetBSD.org/contrib/">http://www.NetBSD.org/contrib/</ulink>. 
</para> 
</sect3>

<sect3 id="xf86-3.3.6-eol">
<title>07 Jan 2005 - XFree86 3.3.6 has been EOLed</title>
<para>
  Matthias Scheler has <ulink
  url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/tech-x11/2005/01/07/0000.html">announced</ulink>
  that XFree86 3.3.6 has been officially EOLed
  in NetBSD-current as of January 7th, 2005:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>Its sources have been removed from
    <quote>xsrc</quote>. They are of course still available via
    CVS.</listitem>
    <listitem>Support for creating XFree86 3.3.6 distribution sets has
    been removed from <quote>src</quote>.</listitem>
    <listitem><filename>bsd.own.mk</filename> now sets
    <varname>USE_XF86_4</varname> to <literal>yes</literal>
    unconditionally.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  All NetBSD ports will use XFree86 4.x based X11 bits in future as they
  already do in the NetBSD 2.0 release.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ts-7200">
<title>04 Jan 2005 - NetBSD/evbarm ported to TS-7200</title>
<para>
   Jesse Off has <ulink
   url="http://mail-index.NetBSD.org/current-users/2005/01/04/0001.html">announced</ulink>
   that he has integrated support for the TS-7200 into the <ulink
   url="../ports/evbarm/">NetBSD/evbarm</ulink> port over the christmas
   holidays.  The TS-7200 is a low-cost mass-produced PC/104 embedded
   single board computer intended as a general purpose core for real embedded
   applications.  More information can be found at <ulink
   url="http://www.embeddedARM.com/~joff/" />.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="newdev200501">
<title>01 Jan 2005 - New Developers</title>
<para>
  The NetBSD project is pleased to welcome the following new developers:
  </para>
  <para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>Stephan Uphoff (login: ups), who will be working on smp and
              threads.</listitem>
    <listitem>Susanne Petra Zeidler (login: spz), who will be working on
              administration, Documentation and odds &amp; ends.</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>
</webpage>
