<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
	 "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">


<webpage id="support-hardware-scsipi">
<config param="desc" value="The NetBSD Foundation"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: scsipi.xml,v 1.2 2008/03/18 14:57:13 reed Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2008/03/18 14:57:13 $"/>
<head>
<title>SCSI and ATAPI Hardware Supported by NetBSD</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="top">
<title>Machine-independent SCSI and ATAPI drivers</title>

<para>
The following devices (<emphasis>driver name in parentheses</emphasis>) 
are supported by machine-independent SCSI and ATAPI drivers. If you do 
not see your device listed here, check your platform's page; there may 
not yet be a machine-independent driver for your device.
</para>

<para>
Alternatively, it may be the case that your device is compatible with one
listed here, or your device may not be listed due to an oversight.  If you
are unsure, please boot a -current kernel or send mail to 
<email>netbsd-users@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>

<para>
Note that SCSI and ATAPI devices are listed together.  This is because
the drivers for the two types of devices are almost completely shared;
ATAPI is more-or-less a way of using an ATA transport for SCSI commands.
</para>

<para>
Please note that these pages reflect the state of NetBSD-current. To check
the supported hardware list for a specific release of NetBSD, check
that release's installation notes.
</para>

<sect2 id="scsipi-devs">
<title>Supported SCSI and ATAPI devices</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem> SCSI and ATAPI CD-ROM drives, and ATAPI CD-ROM drive/changer combos (&man.cd.4;)</listitem>
  <listitem> SCSI media changers, including Archive and HP DAT changers, and
    Exabyte changers (&man.ch.4;)
  </listitem>
  <listitem> SCSI and ATAPI disks and floppies, including SCSI ZIP and Jazz drives,
    and ATAPI ZIP drives, and SCSI RAID arrays which masquerade as a SCSI
    disk (&man.sd.4;)
  </listitem>
  <listitem> SCSI Ethernet interfaces, including the Cabletron EA412 (&man.se.4;)</listitem>
  <listitem> SCSI scanners, including Umax and HP ScanJets (&man.ss.4;)</listitem>
  <listitem> SCSI tape drives (&man.st.4;)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<parentsec url="./" text="Hardware Devices Supported by NetBSD"/>
</webpage>
