<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
 PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
        "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="ports-atari-history">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD/atari History"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: history.xml,v 1.2 2007/06/09 19:18:05 dsieger Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2007/06/09 19:18:05 $"/>
<head>

<!-- Copyright (c) 1996-2007
	The NetBSD Foundation, Inc.  ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. -->

<title>NetBSD/atari History</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="atari_history">
  <para>
    The Atari port of NetBSD became available to the public in
    March 1995. The first formal release was <ulink
    url="http://www.NetBSD.org/releases/formal-1.1/">NetBSD
    1.1</ulink>. The most recent formal release is <ulink
    url="http://www.NetBSD.org/releases/formal-&release.latest.major;/">&os;
    &release.latest;</ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>
    The NetBSD/atari port started out with the NetBSD 1.0 sources. As
    a basis, Leo Weppelman took the Amiga-port, since this port seemed
    to be the best fit to the Atari hardware he had at that time - a
    TT030. This turned out a good starting point and within a few
    months he had something derived that did actually run on his
    TT030.
  </para>

  <para>
    The Atari-port was announced to the NetBSD core team in December
    1994. It still took some time to get it into shape. Finally, at
    the end of March 1995, the Atari port became an initial part of
    NetBSD.
  </para>

  <para>
    At that time, NetBSD/atari only ran on an TT030. It didn't take
    long before requests started coming in for a Falcon port... Making
    the initial Falcon port was a tedious experience for all people
    involved. The problem was that Leo didn't own a Falcon and the
    people owning a Falcon were unable to compile their own kernels
    because they were lacking a decent bootstrap environment (a la
    NetBSD/atari ;-). After lots of retries, the initial problems -
    most of them in the SCSI area - were solved. This took about 5
    tiresome months.
  </para>

  <para>
    Now that the basic building blocks were in place, the time left
    before the first NetBSD release that included Atari support (1.1),
    was spent fixing lots of bugs and smoothing sharp edges.
  </para>

  <para>
    Somewhere in 1996, Leo bought an Hades. Hades support was added at
    the end that year. The Hades architecture opened the door to
    various ISA and PCI cards. NetBSD 1.3 was the first release
    supporting the Hades.
  </para>

  <para>
    The latest addition to the NetBSD/Atari line is the Milan. The
    first, yet still a bit experimental, support was added in NetBSD
    1.6.
  </para>

  <para>
    For those of you that are/were part of the NetBSD/atari history:
  </para>

  <blockquote>
    Hey, look what we did... isn't it great! 
  </blockquote>

</sect1>

<parentsec url="./" text="&os;/atari ports page"/>

</webpage>
