<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="Releases-formal-2.0-NetBSD-2.0.2" release="2.0.2">
<config param="desc" value="NetBSD 2.0.2 Release Announcement"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: NetBSD-2.0.2.xml,v 1.8 2007/01/23 21:00:22 spz Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2007/01/23 21:00:22 $"/>
<head>
<title>Announcing NetBSD 2.0.2</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="announcing">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
  The NetBSD Project is pleased to announce that update 2.0.2 of the NetBSD
  operating system is now available.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="about-netbsd-2.0.2">
<title>About NetBSD 2.0.2</title>

<para>
NetBSD 2.0.2 is the second security/critical update of
the NetBSD 2.0 release branch. This represents a selected subset of fixes
deemed critical in nature for stability or security reasons. 
</para>

<para>
This is also the first binary security/critical update since NetBSD
2.0.  NetBSD 2.0.1 was tagged within the CVS repository, and is            
available from there as a source update, but its full binary release      
was preempted by patches incorporated into 2.0.2 and build hardware
issues.
</para>
<para>
All fixes in security/critical updates (ie, NetBSD 2.0.1, 2.0.2, etc)
are cumulative, so the latest update contains all such fixes since the
corresponding minor release.  These fixes will also appear in future
minor releases (ie, NetBSD 2.1, 2.2, etc), together with other
less-critical fixes and feature enhancements.
</para>
<para>
Complete source and binaries for NetBSD 2.0.2 are available for download at
many sites around the world. A list of download sites providing FTP, AnonCVS,
SUP, and other services is provided at the end of this announcement; the
latest list of available download sites may also be found at:
</para>
<blockquote>
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/mirrors/"/>
</blockquote>
<para>
We encourage users who wish to install via a CD-ROM ISO image to download via
BitTorrent by using the <ulink url="../../mirrors/torrents/">torrent
files</ulink> supplied in the ISO image area. BitTorrent has recently been
added to the list of distribution mechanisms and its use is strongly
encouraged to help keep bandwidth available.
</para>
<!--
<para>
A list of hashes for the NetBSD 2.0.2 distribution has been signed with
the well-connected PGP key for the NetBSD Security-Officer:         
</para>
<blockquote>
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/security/hashes/NetBSD-2.0.2_hashes.asc"/>
</blockquote>
-->
</sect1>

<sect1 id="about-netbsd">
<title>About NetBSD</title>

<para>
The NetBSD operating system is a full-featured, open source, UNIX-like
operating system descended from the Berkeley Networking Release 2 (Net/2),
4.4BSD-Lite, and 4.4BSD-Lite2. NetBSD runs on 54 different system
architectures featuring 17 machine architectures across 17 distinct CPU
families, and is being ported to more. The NetBSD 2.0.2 release contains
complete binary releases for 48 different machine types.     
</para>
<para>
NetBSD is a highly integrated system. In addition to its highly portable,
high performance kernel, NetBSD features a complete set of user utilities,
compilers for several languages, the X Window System, firewall software and
numerous other tools, all accompanied by full source code. The NetBSD       
Packages Collection contains over 5000 packages and binary package releases
for a number of platforms are currently in progress.
</para>
<para>
More information on the goals of the NetBSD Project can be procured from the
NetBSD web site at:
</para>
<blockquote>
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/Goals/"/>
</blockquote>
<para>
NetBSD is free. All of the code is under non-restrictive licenses, and may be
used without paying royalties to anyone. Free support services are available
via our mailing lists and web site. Commercial support is available from a
variety of sources; some are listed at:
</para>
<blockquote>
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/gallery/consultants.html"/>
</blockquote>
<para>
More extensive information on NetBSD is available from the NetBSD web site:
</para>
<blockquote>
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
</blockquote>
<para>
NetBSD is the work of a diverse group of people spread around the world. The
<quote>Net</quote> in our name is a tribute to the Internet, which
enables us to communicate and share code, and without which the
project would not exist.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="major-changes">
<title>Major Changes Between 2.0 and 2.0.2</title>

<para>
The complete list of changes can be found in the <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/NetBSD-2.0.2/CHANGES-2.0.1">CHANGES-2.0.1</ulink>
and <ulink
url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/NetBSD/NetBSD-2.0.2/CHANGES-2.0.2">CHANGES-2.0.2</ulink>
files in the top level doc directory of the NetBSD 2.0.2 release tree.
</para>
<para>
The complete list is as follows:
</para>

<sect2 id="kernel">
<title>Kernel</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>Avoid endless loop in F_CLOSEM &man.fcntl.2; which could be
	 abused for a local DOS.</listitem>
  <listitem>Avoid possible security issues on <port>amd64</port>,
         <port>i386</port> and <port>xen</port> by properly
         checking range for &man.copyinstr.9; and
         &man.copyoutstr.9;.</listitem>
  <listitem>Make pmap_map() work on sun4 machines so these are usable
         again.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix a UVM problem that causes hangs when large processes
         fork.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix pthreads on sun4c hardware by fixing a problem with detecting
         faults in atomic load/store instructions.</listitem>
  <listitem>Address further pthread issues on <port>sparc</port> and
         <port>sparc64</port> by defining a new
         LWP flag which indicates that we're in the process of doing a context
         switch.</listitem>
  <listitem>Make <port>sun3</port> port functional again by restoring the definition for MAXPHYS
         as it is now used rather than MAXBSIZE to limit page cache I/O
         sizes.</listitem>
  <listitem>Prevent lockups/panics if the &man.VOP.LOOKUP.9; call unlocked
         the parent directory node.</listitem>
  <listitem>Prevent a kernel panic on boot with a PX graphics card on
         DECstations.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix <port>prep</port> port to be functional by ensuring that the OpenPIC register
         window is mapped during startup.</listitem>
  <listitem>Clear freed memory in &man.cgd.4; code to avoid possibly security issues.</listitem>
  <listitem>Prevent panics on powerpc with DIAGNOSTIC kernels and trap handling.</listitem>
  <listitem>Make the <port>macppc</port> INSTALL kernel bootable again by 
  moving the load address to the correct location.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix a major issue with <port>sparc64</port> &man.pmap.9; to
	 prevent crashes under heavy load.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix major performance issue with <port>xen</port> port so idle loop doesn't
         consume 100% of CPU time.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix <port>xen</port> port so it can reboot cleanly instead of
         hanging.</listitem>
  <listitem>MMU fixes for <port>sh3</port> based ports to prevent reboots under heavy
         load.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="networking">
<title>Networking</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>Disabled the oow test in &man.ipf.4; because it is killing valid
         packets.</listitem>
  <listitem>Prevent deadlock/panic on NFS clients after NFS server reboots and
         caches aren't in sync.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix an NFS panic caused by truncating a file while another client is
         writing data to it.</listitem>
  <listitem>Avoid infinite loops when getting NFS &man.readdir.3; response
         without any entries or EOF.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix possible remote DOS via IPsec AH packets.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix major performance issues with the i82547 Gig-E chip which
         improves performance with &man.wm.4;.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix problems with &man.sk.4; performance on ASUS A8V
         motherboards.</listitem>
  <listitem>Prevent panics in &man.ipf.4; when receiving IPv6
         packets.</listitem>
  <listitem>NFS fixes to address incorrect atimes updates and cache coherency
         issues.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="system-administration">
<title>System administration and user tools</title>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>Teach &man.groff.1; about NetBSD versions that aren't on the 
         branches documentation.</listitem>
  <listitem>Add description for Solaris 10 dual boot installation.</listitem>
  <listitem>Document PTHREAD_CONCURRENCY.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix bug in binutils which broke Firefox under
         <port>sparc64</port>.</listitem>
  <listitem>Address xpm security problems reported in
         CAN-2005-0605.</listitem>
  <listitem>Fix &man.swapcontext.3; for <port>amd64</port> so that it works
         correctly.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<para>
Please note that at the moment, sysinst will not assist you in installing
pre-built third-party binary packages or the pkgsrc system itself. See the
NetBSD packages collection documentation:
</para>

    <blockquote>
    <ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/Documentation/pkgsrc/"/>
    </blockquote>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="acknowledgements">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>

<para> 
The NetBSD Foundation would like to thank all those who have contributed code,
hardware, documentation, funds, colocation for our servers, web pages and     
other documentation, release engineering, and other resources over the years. 
More information on the people who make NetBSD happen is available at:        
</para>

<blockquote>
<ulink url="http://www.NetBSD.org/People/"/>
</blockquote>

<para>
We would like to especially thank the University of California at Berkeley and
the GNU Project for particularly large subsets of code that we use. We would   
also like to thank the Internet Systems Consortium and the Helsinki
University of Technology for current colocation services.         
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="about-tnf">
<title>About the NetBSD Foundation</title>

<para>
The NetBSD Foundation was chartered in 1995, with the task of overseeing core
NetBSD project services, promoting the project within industry and the open
source community, and holding intellectual property rights on much of the
NetBSD code base. Day-to-day operations of the project are handled by
volunteers.    
</para>
<para>          
As a non-profit organisation with no commercial backing, The NetBSD
Foundation depends on donations from its users, and we would like to ask      
you to consider making a donation to the NetBSD Foundation in support of 
continuing production of our fine operating system.  Your generous           
donation would be particularly welcome at this point in time, since the
release engineering process for NetBSD 2.0 was unfortunately set back
by hardware failures on the build machines, necessitating the immediate
replacement of the equipment.
</para>
<para>          
Donations can be done via PayPal (<email>paypal@NetBSD.org</email>) and are fully          
tax-deductible in the US.  If you would prefer not to use PayPal, or
would like to make other arrangements, please contact
<email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="mirrors">
<title>NetBSD mirror sites</title>

<para>
Please use a mirror site close to you. 
</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#ftp">FTP</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#iso">ISO images</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#anoncvs">Anonymous CVS</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#bittorrent">BitTorrent</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#sup">SUP</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#cvsup">CVSup</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#rsync">rsync</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#afs">AFS</ulink></listitem>
  <listitem><ulink url="../../mirrors/#nfs">NFS</ulink></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Please also note our <ulink url="../../Sites/cdroms.html">list of CD-ROM vendors</ulink>.
</para>
</sect1>

<parentsec url="./" text="NetBSD 2.0 formal releases"/>
</webpage>
