<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
	 "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd">

<webpage id="donations-index">
<config param="desc" value="donations"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: index.xml,v 1.17 2007/03/12 23:24:50 wennmach Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2007/03/12 23:24:50 $"/>
<head>
<title>Donations to The NetBSD Foundation</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="why">
<title id="why.title">Why donations are important</title>
<para>
The NetBSD Foundation is a non-profit organization that produces open
source software, and has Internal Revenue Code 501(c)(3) status.
This means that it has no regular source of income,
instead relying on generous donations from third parties.
</para>

<para>
Funding for the NetBSD Foundation comes from a variety of sources.
Organizations and individuals interested in NetBSD contribute money,
hardware and rack space to support important NetBSD Foundation services,
and to enable developers to support new hardware platforms and peripherals.
</para>

<para>
It's important to understand that every donation matters. Without servers
and rack space at colocation facilities, we would not be able to provide
high-quality services such as regular builds and the various web and
FTP services to our developers and users. Without donations of development
hardware, we would not be able to support the huge range of
<ulink url="../Ports/">platforms</ulink> and
<ulink url="../Hardware/">peripherals</ulink> we do today. Promotional work
at events enables us to present our work to others and acquire new
developers and users. Each of these functions is important to the ongoing
health of the NetBSD Foundation.
</para>

<para>
So, whether you're a Fortune 100 company shipping NetBSD in a product, a
company running your web server on NetBSD, a home user with NetBSD on your
desktop, or just someone who thinks NetBSD is cool &#8212; or all four
&#8212; please consider donating something to the NetBSD Foundation.
</para>

<para>
There are, of course, other ways that both <ulink
url="../contrib/howto.html">individuals</ulink> and <ulink
url="../contrib/org/help.html">organizations</ulink> can contribute to
The NetBSD Foundation.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="how-to-donate">
<title id="how-to-donate.title">Making a donation to The NetBSD Foundation</title>
<para>
The simplest way to donate is monetarily, via PayPal. If you would
prefer not to use PayPal, or would like to make other arrangements,
please contact <email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>
<para>
  <emphasis role="bold">All donations to the NetBSD Foundation are fully
   tax-deductible in the US!</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
PayPal is essentially an online bank that allows its users to easily
transfer money among each other.  You do not need to have a PayPal
account to use PayPal to send money to NetBSD; you can use a credit
card on PayPal's site to send funds directly to the NetBSD PayPal
account, or you can use funds from your own PayPal account if you
have one.  The PayPal address for NetBSD is <email>paypal@NetBSD.org</email>.
The PayPal site will guide you through all the steps you need to take to
open an account and send money.
</para>

<para>
To donate using PayPal, start here:

<html:form action="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr" method="post">
<html:input type="hidden" name="cmd" value="_xclick"/>
<html:input type="hidden" name="business" value="paypal@NetBSD.org"/>
<html:input type="hidden" name="item_name" value="The NetBSD Foundation"/>
<html:input type="hidden" name="no_shipping" value="1"/>
<html:input type="hidden" name="return" value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
<html:input type="hidden" name="cancel_return" value="http://www.NetBSD.org/"/>
<html:input type="image" src="http://images.paypal.com/images/x-click-but04.gif" name="submit" alt="Make payments with PayPal - it's fast, free and secure!"/>
</html:form>
</para>

<sect2 id="link-policy">
<title id="link-policy.title">Donation Policy</title>

<para>
The NetBSD Foundation has a policy of acknowledging donors on their
web pages (see below). After we received your donation, we will
send you an acknowledgement letter, containing a confirmation section
for the IRS and a small questionnaire about how you wish your entry
to appear on the donor web pages.
</para>

<para>
Please note that as of 2007-03-15, links to donor URLs will be put up
only for donations that exceed $50.00 USD. Normally the link to the donor
URL will be established after a delay of one month.
</para>

<para>
If you have any questions about the donation process or if you want or
don't want your name to be added to the <ulink url="2006.html">list of
contributors</ulink>, please let us know at
<email>finance-exec@NetBSD.org</email>.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="contributors">
<title id="contributors.title">Past and ongoing contributors</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><ulink url="2007.html">Donations in 2007</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="2006.html">Donations in 2006</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="2005.html">Donations in 2005</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="2004.html">Donations in 2004</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="2003.html">Donations in 2003</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="../contrib/org/">Organizations, 2002 and earlier</ulink></listitem>
<listitem><ulink url="../contrib/donations.html">Individuals, 2002 and earlier</ulink></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

</webpage>
