<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE webpage
  PUBLIC "-//NetBSD//DTD Website-based NetBSD Extension//EN"
         "http://www.NetBSD.org/XML/htdocs/lang/share/xml/website-netbsd.dtd" [
]>

<webpage id="contrib-org-help">
<config param="desc" value="How an organisation can assist NetBSD"/>
<config param="cvstag" value="$NetBSD: help.xml,v 1.4 2005/07/16 17:13:51 heinz Exp $"/>
<config param="rcsdate" value="$Date: 2005/07/16 17:13:51 $"/>
<head>
<title>How an organisation can assist NetBSD</title>
</head>

<sect1 id="top">

<para>
We are in the process of compiling a <ulink
url="./">gallery</ulink> of companies that assist the
project in any of the following fashions, and would be very much
interested in hearing from you at &lt;<ulink
url="mailto:www@NetBSD.org">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>&gt;.
</para>

<sect2 id="hardware">
<title>If your organisation produces hardware</title>

<para>
From interface cards to complete machines, two of the greatest
hurdles to supporting hardware are availability of technical
documentation, and access to the hardware itself. If your organisation
can provide either of these to NetBSD developers it can help NetBSD
users worldwide, and benefit your company image.
</para>

<para>
Those companies that wish to assist further can contribute specific
code for drivers which can reduce the NetBSD 'time to market' for
the product and ensure the hardware is used to its full advantage.
</para>

<para>
A statement as to the degree of support available for NetBSD can
increase NetBSD users' confidence in selecting a given product.
Even if direct support is not available, information as to in-house
testing with NetBSD will encourage users to choose a product over
a competitor who does not perform such testing.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="other-methods">
<title>Other methods of assisting NetBSD</title>

<para>
Some of the other options are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Directly donate <ulink url="../hardware.html">hardware</ulink>, or
    financial aid to the project.</listitem>
<listitem>Become a NetBSD <ulink url="../../mirrors/">mirror</ulink> site.</listitem>
<listitem>Finance specific hardware support or features (see the
 <ulink url="../../gallery/consultants.html">consultants</ulink> gallery)</listitem>
<listitem>Hire a NetBSD developer to work on in house NetBSD projects.</listitem>
<listitem>Many of the <ulink url="../howto.html">same methods</ulink> open to ordinary users.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If you have any questions related to the above, please let us know at
&lt;<ulink url="mailto:www@NetBSD.org">www@NetBSD.org</ulink>&gt;.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

</webpage>
